Chapter 2

The next point of significance in my story is a conversation that I had with Dixon in the nursing home after my accident, a few days before I was taken back to my own house.

He came and sat beside my bed one morning when he had examined me and the nurse had gone away; he must have had an easy round that day. “I’m going to move you back into your own house next week, I think,” he said. “Would you like that?”

I was as weak as a kitten. I had a continuous headache, and I was pretty miserable at night. I told him this, and said that I didn’t think that I was fit to go.

He eyed me seriously. “You don’t get over an accident like this in a day, or in two days, you know,” he said. “For one thing, you evidently lost a great deal of blood from the wound in your head. Quite apart from the concussion.”

Irrelevantly I cut him short and asked what I had wanted to know for some days now. “What’s happened to my car?”

“It’s been taken down to Walker’s garage and they’re waiting for your instructions before beginning on it. I saw it the day after the accident, and I was very much interested.”

I asked: “Is she very much knocked about?”

“The radiator and the wings were very badly damaged,” he replied, “and there was a lot of glass broken. But I found the most interesting part to be the hole in the fabric of the roof over the driver’s seat, where your head had hit. Your head must have gone very nearly through the roof—I never saw such a thing. You must consider yourself very fortunate that it was not a coach–built body.”

I was quiet for a time. “It’s a hundred–and–fifty–pound job, I suppose,” I said at last, a little painfully. “She must need re–upholstering with all that blood and muck.”

He wrinkled up his brows a little. “I doubt if she does,” he said. “There was a little mess on the roof, but the inside of the car was quite clean. I think you must have done your bleeding out of the window. She was lying on her side, you see.”

I asked: “How long was I there?”

“A labourer found you on his way to work—one of the men on Halls Farm at Stoke Fleming. He must have found you at about half–past six. When did you leave Plymouth?”

I tried to recollect. “I think it must have been about half–past twelve.”

He nodded. “You must have been lying there for about five hours. You know, seriously, you’re extremely lucky to have come out of it so well. You might very well have died in that five hours.”

I said: “Providence looks after fools and drunken men.”

He stared at me, and nodded again. “Yes. You may have been a fool—I don’t know about that. But I do know that you were drunk.”

“So do I,” I said, a little shortly.

There was a little silence then. He sat tapping his pince–nez on the palm of his hand and eyeing me, till at last he said: “You know, you’re simply knocking yourself to bits. It’s time you pulled up and lived like everybody else.”

“Damn it, man,” I said. “You talk as if I was a bloody dipsomaniac.”

He was patient. “I didn’t mean your drinking. I mean just this—that you’re knocking yourself to bits. You don’t take care of yourself. Do you, now?”

I lay and stared at him, half expecting to see him furtively consult his notes. He was not at all at his ease, and suddenly it seemed to me that he’d set himself a job that he didn’t like doing. “You’d better tell me what you mean,” I said.

He cleared his throat, and considered for a moment. “I don’t know that I’ve ever had a case quite like you. I’ve never had a patient of your general physique through my hands so often as you, and with such a variety of ailments. Just look at them. You broke your arm in two places last summer in the races, and very nearly lost it, I may say.”

“Gybing in the devil of a sea,” I put in. “You can’t always rely on a vessel when she’s like that—especially if she’s over–canvassed for racing. You know that.”

He nodded. “That’s why every other boat but you made a wheelbarrow tack at the buoy. Then, the winter before, you managed to turn a simple touch of flu into a pleurisy, simply because you wouldn’t lie up.”

“I had some work to do,” I said. “That might have happened to anyone.”

“The point is, that it doesn’t. Then, before that, you got water on the knee—not very serious, but you neglected it; and it’s only the mercy of Providence that you’re not lame yet. Frankly, at the time, I thought that it was becoming chronic.”

He paused. “Do you know that you’ve been in my hands six times in the last two years? And it’s only for want of a little care.”

I hadn’t much to say that was worth saying. “I’ve been a pretty good source of income to you, taking it by and large,” I said. “As good as half a dozen old ladies. You don’t want me to mend my ways?”

I must have stung him up, somehow. “Well,” he said drily, “I want you to go on being a source of income to me, anyway.”

There was a little silence.

“I see,” I said. “You think I’m a bad life.”

He thought about it for a moment. “No, I don’t. I didn’t like that pleurisy at all. You’ve not got the resistance that you ought to have, but that’s the infection you picked up in the war. But if you take care of yourself, I see no reason at all why you shouldn’t live to be seventy or eighty.”

“God forbid,” I muttered.

He was annoyed. “On the other hand, if you carry on as you’re doing now, you’ll probably be dead within the next five years. You’ll gybe in a squall when there isn’t a motor boat to pick you up, or you’ll get a pleurisy when I’m not there, or you’ll crash your car where labourers don’t come. And then you’ll die.”

“Yes,” I said. “That’s very likely what will happen.”

He was a little disconcerted and lost the thread of his argument. I lay there staring out of the window while he was marshalling his fancies into order again and I heard a steamer’s siren from the river, a sharp double blast. “You might have a look and see what vessel that is,” I said.

He stood up. “A little collier. About five hundred tons.”

I was interested. “The Black Prince?”

He shook his head. “I don’t know them. She’s got one black funnel with a double blue band.” And then he turned from the window and stood looking down on me, his back to the light, his hands in his pockets. “You know,” he said, “speaking as your medical man, I should advise you to get married.”

I was hardly listening. It was the bi–weekly collier from Barry, but she must have had a good passage, because she had saved a tide. Old Penrose, who had had her since the war, had retired a month or so before and the owners had given the command to his nephew, who used to be her mate; a smart young chap who wore a brown bowler hat with his reefer jacket when he came ashore. I wondered if he had taken to forcing her in good weather, and whether she would stand it. Then I came back to earth and Dixon was talking at me still.

He was very earnest. “I don’t know that I’ve ever recommended this before—to anyone. But it’s what you need.”

I eyed him for a minute, and he didn’t like it. “You think so?”

He said: “I think so. Living alone as you do, you’re simply knocking yourself to bits. And you don’t care a damn about it—do you?”

“No,” I said. “I don’t know that I do.”

He came and sat down beside my bed again. “Look here, Stevenson,” he said. “I want you to realise that you’re a case to me, and nothing more. This is a matter of business to me. I’m not trying to ferret round among your private affairs; I don’t know anything about them, and I don’t want to. I’m not trying to get at you. All I want to tell you is that, as your medical adviser, I should advise you to get married. I think if you did that, you wouldn’t find yourself in my hands quite so often.”

I nodded. “You mean that I ought to get someone to look after me,” I said. “I expect you’re right.”

He was relieved. “I’m glad you see it like that,” he said frankly, “because I don’t like giving this sort of advice at all. I was afraid that you might think it a considerable impertinence.”

“Not at all,” I murmured. “Who do you suggest that I should get?”

He smiled. “Anyone you like. There are any number of nice girls about who’d be only too glad to get married to a man of your position and your means. You won’t have any difficulty in that way.”

“Yes,” I said quietly. “I’ve got the money. And that’s all that really matters, isn’t it?”

He hesitated. “It goes a long way,” he said.

I agreed. “It does. I can pay for anything I want. You produce the medicine, and I’ll pay for it all right.”

He laughed. “I’m a doctor—not a matrimonial agency. I can’t go chasing round the country finding girls for you to marry. But I can promise you, you won’t have any difficulty. Any girl would marry you. You must realise that you’re a very eligible man.”

There was a little silence then. Dixon was right, of course, in what he said; I had realised it myself five years before. A man who lives entirely without women has only two alternatives as the years go on. He gets self–centred and dirty, or he dies.

I laughed. “All right,” I said at last, “I’ll have Irene. I suppose she’ll do as well as anyone. You might tell her when you go home. You’d better send her up to me this afternoon.”

I forgot all that he said to that, nor am I sure that I should write it down if I could remember it; he was very deeply hurt. His wife was dead and he had only the one daughter, and a son who was abroad. I had known the girl for some years by sight; I had watched her grow from a gawky schoolgirl into a plump and homely young woman who kept house admirably for her father, performed indifferently on the tennis courts, rode a bicycle about the town, and read some woman’s paper from cover to cover every week. A most estimable young woman and as dull as ditch–water, but he thought the world of her.

He went away, very grieved and hurt. On reflection I thought that he might see a certain element of humour in the situation; but when he came again he was cold and professional, and I didn’t stir him up.

I got back into my house in the following week, and as soon as I got back I went to work. Dixon was pretty rude about it—and to do him justice, I don’t think it did me a lot of good, myself. I used to go down to my office at about ten o’clock and dictate a few letters that Tillotson would generally have to correct for me, and I would listen to him while he outlined his plans for the freight programme in a series of delicately–worded suggestions for my approval. Then I would send him away and sit in my office for a bit with my head in my hands, nursing a tearing headache; at half–past eleven Miss Soames would bring me a cup of tea and I’d take a handful of aspirins with it, and go for a walk round the yard. By then it would be time for a couple of drinks before lunch, and after lunch there were generally things that needed my attention in the yard. It was during that time that Thelma came in with her bitts carried away, warping at Fowey for the clay. That kept me busy for three days and sent me a journey to Newton Abbot to pick the timber that I wanted for the job, but mostly I spent the afternoons setting up new running gear in Runagate, and trying not to think about my head.

I might have stayed at home for all the good I was. But down at the yard there were things happening and people to talk to; I’ve never been one for sticking in the house by myself, much.

My car took about a month to repair; in that month my cousin Joan Stenning became Lady Stenning. Stenning received his knighthood within half an hour of his landing on the Thames, having sweated and cursed his way through his forty–thousand–mile flight alone round the world in the little Rawdon Dabchick flying–boat. He took nine months over the flight, which was more of a business trip than anything else, and he returned with orders for over a hundred Dabchicks, booked upon the way. He took a cinema camera with him and made films which were worth a considerable sum; his machine was literally plastered with the advertisements of the firms who had supplied him with equipment free. His flight showed a profit of six hundred per cent on the capital involved, an achievement only comparable with that of his progenitor, Sir Francis Drake.

His knighthood created a situation in my family which was not without its quiet humour. Joan had married him in 1925, and had gone to live with him in Golders Green, in undistinguished style. The family didn’t like it a bit, Stenning was a professional pilot, and for a long time after their marriage, if you flew from London to Paris, the chances were that you would see him sitting patiently in the cockpit of the aeroplane, high above your head, as you embarked. Even now, if you go to the Rawdon Aircraft Company to charter an aeroplane the chances are that you will be chauffeured by a Knight of the British Empire. The material profits of his flight went mostly to the financiers who had backed him, leaving him with little but his knighthood and experience.

My family didn’t quite know what to do about it. Sir Philip Stenning could no longer be ignored; it was no longer possible to refer to Lady Stenning as poor Joan. I wrote to congratulate him, and got a letter back from Joan in which she asked if I would like to run her up to Scotland for a week.

I really wasn’t fit to drive again, but I wanted that holiday with Joan. It took me two days to get to London because I had to stop in Shaftesbury and go to bed. Stenning had gone to Greece to try to get rid of a few more Dabchicks. I hadn’t let anyone know that I’d been ill, but Joan was very decent about it, and after a couple of days we set off up north, Joan driving the Bentley.

We got to the MacEwens’ at Carthness in time for dinner on the second day; if I had been fit we should have done it in a day and not been tired. I stayed up there for ten days playing golf with Joan, and sailing their dinghy, and watching the birds. In that ten days my headaches went away, and I never got them back again. I get over these things pretty quickly as a rule.

Joan was up there for a month, but ten days was all that I could spare from the yard, and so I started off for home one morning in the Bentley. I took it easily because Joan had made me promise to spend two nights upon the way, and as she had been decent and not worried me about the crash I was inclined to keep my promise to her.

By six o’clock I was at Boroughbridge and wondering where I should put up for the night. York was not very far away, but I had stayed at York on the way up in a very famous hotel with faded lace curtains in the dining–room, and had not been impressed. And so for a whim, and because I wanted to see people of the sort that I do not usually meet, I went to Leeds and stayed in a very large and rather garish hotel in the middle of the town.

I was very lonely that night. I had left people who liked me in Scotland to come back down south to my empty house and to my own work, and though I knew that I should be content with my life when I got back to Dartmouth, for the moment I was discontented and upset. I dined alone and rather expensively in the more select of the two restaurants of the hotel, and at the table beside me there was a party of young men and women dining not wisely but too well. In the south they would have been thrown out with the hors d’œuvres, but they were having the devil of a good time and I would have given my eyes to have been with them. There were two or three parties of elderly business men with their unattractive wives drinking champagne in solemn state, and there were two or three fat, elderly foreigners dining alone like me and, like me, trying to pretend that they were enjoying their dinner. I got tired of the pretence half–way through and cut it short, ordered a cup of coffee, and went out.

In the hall one of the waiters found me a cigar. I hung about there for a bit and managed to get into conversation with the hall porter, and was pleased to do so. He told me about the theatres that were on and I didn’t like the idea of any of them, and then he started on the cinemas. And finally he said:

“There’s a good Palais de Dance if you’re fond of dancing, sir. Quite a good class place tonight. This is the two–shilling night, you know.”

I don’t dance more than once or twice a year, but I am very fond of it. This was something rather new to me, and so I said:

“They have professional partners there?”

He smiled fatly. “Oh, yes, sir. Sixpennies, you know. Sixpence a dance, or sixpence a sit out, which ever you happens to prefer. Nice respectable young ladies they are—mostly.”

I nodded. The more I thought about it the more I liked the idea. I could not face the thought of going through the evening alone, but for a pound or so I could hire a girl to spend the evening with me. For once in a way my money was some good to me, and so I went upstairs and changed my shoes, and went out to the Palais.

I sat at a table by the floor for some time before dancing. It must have been a pretty slack night at the Palais, because there cannot have been more than a dozen couples in the place. The sixpennies sat in a pen in the corner, smoking cigarettes and reading magazines; four or five girls in black silk dresses and the same number of slight effeminate young men in dinner–jackets. There was one girl there that I liked the look of most, a little older than the rest, perhaps, and one who looked as if she wouldn’t be much effort for me to entertain. And so at last I walked up to the barrier and caught her eye, and I said: “Would you care to dance this one with me?”

She glanced quickly up and down the little row of girls; a sort of commercial rectitude that insisted that she must be quite sure that the invitation was to her, and not to her neighbour. And then she looked up at me and smiled, and said:

“Me? I’d like to very much.”

So we danced, and she asked me if I had been long in Leeds, and I made the usual talk about the band and the floor and my own dancing, and she gave little stilted answers. And suddenly it struck me that she was busy, almost too busy to talk. Then I fell over her feet and she said quickly: “Would you do that again?” I did it again, but her feet weren’t there that time. It took her about a minute and a half to learn my tricks. By the end of that quickstep I could do exactly what I liked; she danced magnificently. The dance came to a truncated end and the short encore; I walked her off the floor and put her back into the pen.

Three minutes later I got her out again for a waltz. Again she was busy at first, so that I left her alone and we danced that one in silence. I was taking her back to the pen again when she turned to me and said:

“You know, you don’t need to put me back in the pen again after every dance unless you want to. They let us go and sit with gentlemen at the tables, if you like.”

I said something suitable, and so we picked a table and sat down. And hardly was my chair drawn in when she remarked:

“Would you like anything from the soda fountain? A cup of coffee or anything? I’ll fetch the waitress for you, if you like.”

So I ordered a cup of coffee for her; she would not eat anything because eating between meals was bad for the figure. Then I bought her cigarettes. Then we danced again, and coming back to the table I had leisure to examine what I’d got.

She was not very tall, perhaps a little higher than my shoulder. She had long black hair tied up in coils about her ears and drawn straight back from her forehead; she was extravagantly made up with a dead white complexion and deep red lips. She had very large, black eyes and rather a determined chin; when she smiled she was very friendly to me. Her eyelashes were separated into little groups, very long, each group waxed together like a little moustache. She wore a plain black silk dress and a very small gold watch upon her wrist.

I said what a pretty little watch it was; she was pleased, and took it off to show it to me. “A gentleman friend gave it to me,” she said, “when I was working at Leicester. He was nice to me—isn’t it lovely? It cost six pounds fifteen, and then he got something off because it was through a friend in the business. Another gentleman told me that you couldn’t buy a watch like this for under ten pounds. Fancy! But lots of the gentlemen give us quite nice presents.” I murmured something or other, and for a moment she paused to appraise my value. “He was married, but his wife used to go away a lot and then he got lonely and used to come and spend the evening with me. Are you married?”

“No,” I said, “I’m not. Are you?”

She studied me for a moment through a haze of smoke. “No,” she said at last, “nor anywhere near it.”

She told me that her name was Miss Gordon, but her friends called her Mollie. “I do think it’s soft,” she said, “when professionals make up fancy names for themselves, like Edwina or Althea, like some of them do.” She laughed. “Fancy me talking like that! I mean, they call me Carmen here on Friday nights, because I do a speciality dance then—tango—I’ve got a lovely costume for it. I do it with one of the boys here, and he’s in costume too.” Then we talked about her profession; she told me that she was paid ten shillings a week and half the sixpences she earned. “But then there’s the tips,” she said, with studied nonchalance. “Some of the gentlemen are very generous. Then other times you’ll dance all night with a gentleman and never get a bean beyond the sixpences.”

She told me a little about her pay. It was a good week when she took home thirty shillings from the management; living by herself alone in rooms she could hardly have got along without the tips. I was sorry then that I had made her dig so laboriously for her gold, and so I said:

“How do the tips run out? Do people double the sixpences, or something like that?”

She looked across the table at me with something that was very much like friendship. “Not many,” she said generously. “You see, that comes to an awful lot if you dance all evening.” She eyed me for a moment. “You’ve not been to a Palais much, have you? It must be expensive for the gentlemen, having us girls for every dance. Would you like me to go back to the pen and dance again a bit later? Lots of people do that, you know.”

“Rather not,” I said. “I’ve got money to spend tonight, and I’m just beginning to enjoy myself.”

She laughed with me. “I like it when people have a good time here,” she said, “because it makes it much nicer, doesn’t it?” And then she asked me: “What’s your job?”

“I work for a shipping firm in the south,” I said. “I’m in the office.”

She nodded, and we went and danced again. She was immensely clever at her job, very cunning in suiting her ways to mine. And presently she began to educate me a little in the finer points of her peculiar art. When that happened I knew that she was beginning to enjoy herself.

She said no more about money, apparently satisfied that it was going to be all right at the end of the evening. She told me a little about her life; it seemed that she had been brought up for the stage in some fifth–rate theatrical school. For a few years she had scratched a livelihood by occasional engagements in the chorus of provincial companies; then she had abandoned that for dancing and had wandered in a desultory manner from Palais to Palais, staying perhaps six months in each. She told me that her home was in Preston.

“It’s not much fun being on the stage,” she said, “when you’re out of a job most of the time. I’d rather do this. I’ve been in quite a lot of Palais since I started. Bournemouth was lovely—I was a silly to come away from there. But there was a gentleman….” She stared absently across the floor, then roused herself and turned to me. “Sometimes one gets mixed up in a place,” she said quietly, “and then it’s time to move on.”

I nodded. “How do you like Leeds?”

She shrugged her shoulders. “I don’t think I’ll be here very much longer. I want to get down to the south again, with the summer coming on. Tell me, have you ever been to Torquay?”

“I know it pretty well,” I said. “It’s not far from where I work.”

She turned to me: “Is it lovely?” And then, without waiting for my answer, she went on: “I’d love to go to Torquay. I’ve never been, but everybody says it’s lovely there. One of the girls here went there for her holiday last year with a gentleman, and she said it was lovely. It’s all on hills, isn’t it, looking out over the sea, with a harbour and boats and things?”

“That’s it,” I said. “The shops are all along by the harbour.”

She sighed. “I’d love to get into a Palais there. It must be lovely to live in a place like that. But they don’t get many vacancies in those places. The girls down there, they know when they’re well off.”

We danced again, and came back to the table.

“Been to many shows?” she asked.

I tried to remember when I had last been at the theatre. “Not many lately,” I replied. “I expect you go to lots. Or can’t you get away from here?”

She blew a long cloud of smoke. “It’s not very easy. You see, if you get a boy that wants to take you out he has to book you out for the session, and that costs twenty–five bob on top on what he spends outside. It’s only the old ones that can do that, and I don’t like going out with them. They get so silly. But I do love a show, better than anything. I expect you don’t care for them much?”

I had had a long drive that day, and a good dinner. I was leaving Leeds on the next day, and it was unlikely that I should ever see this girl again. Sometimes it’s a luxury to speak the truth. “I like a theatre,” I said. “I like to go and have a really good dinner somewhere, and go on to a theatre, and then go and dance for an hour or so before bed. But you want to have somebody to go with; it’s not much fun doing that alone.”

She nodded. “Haven’t you got any girl friends to go with?”

I knocked the ash off my cigarette. “No,” I said. “They don’t seem to come my way much.” I looked at her and grinned. “That’s why I have to come and pay sixpence.”

She nodded, without laughing. “You’re too particular,” she said shrewdly. “There’s ever so many like you come and dance with us—you’d be surprised. There’s some that just don’t want to do anything but sit and talk for a bit. It’s like as if they don’t seem able to fancy the girl friends they can get, and can’t get the ones they fancy, and so they come here. It’s funny, isn’t it? My brother now, he’s just the same as you.”

I was watching an unpleasant youth dancing with an anæmic girl, an extraordinarily graceful pair. “What does he do?” I asked absently.

Evidently she was very proud of him. “He’s in the motor transport business. He’s got a lorry of his own. I hadn’t seen him for over three years, and I didn’t know where he was or anything, but he turned up here on Friday last week, and booked me out all Saturday, and we had a lovely time. They told him at home that I was here. He’s doing awfully well, down somewhere in the south. He takes carpet sweepers and things that come from abroad from the boats and drives them to the factory, or something. It’s all–night work.”

She paused. “He’s just the same as you—never seems to fancy the sort of girl that he can pick up.” She bent a hostile eye upon the single ladies sitting at their tables all alone. “And there’s some that don’t take much picking up, either.” She paused. “We always used to do things together when he was home, and it was lovely seeing him again.”

The evening was drawing to a close. I was tired and ready for my bed and I had the suspicion of a headache which I wasn’t anxious to provoke. “I’m going home in a little while,” I said. “Would you like something from the soda fountain before I go? An ice, or anything?”

The hard, painted harridan of our first meeting had merged imperceptibly into the girl friend that she had spoken of. “That ’ld be lovely,” she said. “What can I have?”

“Anything you like,” I said, a little surprised. “What do you want?”

She hesitated. “Some of the things are rather expensive, you know.”

I had never had that said to me by any girl before. I smiled at her. “It’s nearly the end of my holiday,” I said quietly. “I’ve got a lot of money to blue before I go back home.” And she laughed, and said: “If that’s the way of it, I’ll have a banana split.”

So I ordered two of these things, and when the bill came it was half–a–crown. “I told you they were terribly expensive,” she said, a little ruefully. We finished them and went and danced again, and after that I sent her to find out my reckoning for me.

She came back. “It’s twenty–five dances. That’ll be twelve and six, won’t it?” So I gave her twenty–five shillings, feeling that it was miserably inadequate for the evening that she’d given me, and she said: “Oh, that’s an awful lot. You are kind!”

We shook hands. “I’ve enjoyed this frightfully,” I said. “It’s been the nicest evening that I’ve had for years.”

“It has been nice,” she said simply. “I’ve loved it. You’ll come back when you’re in Leeds again, won’t you?”

And so my hostess said goodnight to me, and I went back to my hotel alone. Next morning I set out for home.

Chapter 5

She had a bed–sitting–room in the district rather to the west of Leeds; I found the house next morning with some difficulty. It was in an industrial neighbourhood. It was one of many little streets of drab brick houses, semi–detached and each with a little front garden for the cats; not quite a squalid street, but very nearly so. It was called Acacia Road, and she lived in the house of a man who worked in the goods office at the railway. The road was a playground for the children of the neighbourhood.

It was just after ten o’clock when I drew up before her house; the children swarmed around, staring and fingering the car. She must have been on the look out for me, unseen, because as I got out of the saloon the door of the house opened and she came out to me, suitcase in hand. I went forward to meet her; in the front window a faded blind was pulled aside to disclose a woman’s face pressed close against the glass.

I smiled and took the case from her, bulging a little and cracked and gaping at the corners. I think it had in it all that she possessed, or nearly all. She was in grey; grey shoes, grey stockings, grey overcoat, and grey felt hat; she had taken great pains over the adornment of her face. “It’s going to be fine,” I said. “We’ll have a good run down.”

She hesitated motionless upon the pavement. “Oh!” she said. “Is this your car?”

I never did like little cars, and my Bentley suits me pretty well. A dead, dull black saloon with a silver radiator and fittings, it loomed immensely in that narrow street; it seemed to shame the cramped style of the little villas. She moved forward on the pavement and peered in through the window at the deep, low seats, the hide upholstery and the gleaming wheel. “Oh!” she said. “Is this your car?”

I nodded. “Do you like her?”

She breathed: “It’s awfully grand.” And then she said: “Are you going to drive it yourself?”

She thought, I think, that the driving of a car like that was a professional matter and that lurking somewhere round about would be Adams in his livery, who at that moment was mowing the lawns of the Port House, down in Devonshire. I smiled at her. “I am,” I said. “That is, unless you’d like to take her for a bit, later in the day.”

She shook her head. “I only drove a car once, one day with Billy. He said it was a Morris—Morris something. But I couldn’t drive a car like this.”

I swung her suitcase into the back of the car beside my own and opened the front door for her. “All right,” I said equably. “Then you’ll just have to sit and watch for the best part of three hundred miles.”

She stared at me wide eyed. “Is it as far as that?”

“Something over two–fifty, anyway,” I said. “It may be over three hundred. It’ll take us most of the day, taking things easily. But it’s a good day for a run.”

She hesitated for a moment in the door, examining the car and feeling the upholstery. “I used to go out with a boy who had an Essex coach, in Birmingham,” she remarked. “But that wasn’t like this….”

I thought of Le Mans. “This isn’t quite so handy in a busy street,” I said politely. “It’s too big.” And with that we got into her, and moved away down the road.

We went down through Huddersfield, through a bleak and blackened land of little fields and little mills. Between the towns it was bright and sunny on the road; Sixpence sat quiet by my side. I gave her a map to study, but she couldn’t read it, and so we went on more or less by dead reckoning, eked out by signposts and by my memory of the road. Before we had been going for ten minutes I had absently thrown off my hat into the back seats of the car; I generally drive bareheaded in a saloon.

She turned an eager, delicately–painted little face to me. “May I do that too? Take off my hat, I mean?”

I smiled. “Of course. Better make yourself really comfortable; we’ve got a good way to go.” I reached behind and got her a rug; she took off her hat and patted her hair into shape before the mirror of her bag, powdered her nose, and settled down happily beside me as I drove.

“There’s cigarettes there, if you like,” I said. “You might give me one….” I had to show her how to use the lighter then, and that amused her almost more than anything we saw that day. All morning I was smoking cigarettes; with each cigarette she pressed the button till the unit glowed, lips parted, watching it entranced; then she pulled it out and handed it to me. She couldn’t make out how it worked at all.

I gave the Midlands a miss that day and went down the Welsh side. We got up on the high land after Huddersfield and went across the moors, skirting Manchester, to Buxton; then down to Newcastle–under–Lyme. It was there that Sixpence asked in all innocence if my car was a fast one and we got her up to eighty–six before I had to shut her down for a corner, but mostly we were running at about fifty. We turned away from Staffordshire and cut down through Market Drayton to Shrewsbury, and when we had passed through that we began to think about our lunch.

I chose the Chequers at Church Stretton, a place that I had had meals at before. The house dates back to the sixteenth century; a grey stone building, rather rambling, and full of open fireplaces burning wood. They have restored it and built on a dining–room within the last few years, and spoilt it altogether. They run it as a show place now, with prices commensurate, and no good American goes home without having spent a night in the room where Charles II slept and knighted Perrhyn.

We left the car by the grass plot in front and went into the hall, ushered by a porter in brown livery. I knew that I had made a mistake as soon as I got inside; we should have lunched at some little pub by the roadside. The place was all white paint and glass panels inside, like a hospital; the mere travesty of an English country house. The new dining–room was very white and spacious, with tables round the edge of a bleak dancing floor.

I was occupied with Sixpence at the beginning of our meal, and we had finished the fish before I was free to look about the room. Over in an alcove by the window there was a lady lunching with a couple of children, very neat and clean, in charge of a neat, clean nurse in the uniform of some institute or other. Something about the lady seemed familiar to me and drew my attention; I stared at her a little harder, and it was Marion.

Marion, whom I hadn’t seen or heard of for the last nine years since we parted in the stables down at Courton, crying her eyes out because she didn’t want to marry me. Why she should have cried like that I never understood; if anyone had a right to cry it should have been me, but I can only remember feeling a bit uncomfortable about it all. Nine years is a long time; she had filled out and collected a couple of children, but it was Marion all right. I seemed to remember having heard that she was married; I wondered what her name was now.

Towards the end of lunch the nurse marshalled the children and went out with them, and she was left alone for coffee. I bent across the table to Sixpence.

“I’ve just seen an old friend of mine at that table over there—the lady. Do you mind if I go over and speak to her for a minute or two?” And so I crossed the room to her table.

“Good morning, Marion,” I said quietly. She looked up in surprise; then she recognised me. “Malcolm!” she said. “After all these years. My dear!”

I sat down beside her table and talked with her for a few minutes of the old days and friends that we had known. She had a neat and orderly mind even in the old days; with the years this had grown on her and now she was very social, very rigid in her class. She told me that she was living in the hotel with her two children for the summer ‘because the air was so good for them’; I heard no mention of her husband, nor of any home that they had made. I sat there listening, thinking that I could have done better for her than that.

In turn she wanted to know my news. “There’s nothing much to tell,” I said. “I still live down in Dartmouth, just the same. I have my work down there, you see, and that’s all one really wants.” I smiled. “That,” I said, “and a certain amount to drink.”

She said: “Oh, my dear. Do you mean you’ve never married, all these years?”

I laughed. “Lord, no,” I said; “nor likely to. You should know that.”

She said: “Oh, Malcolm!”

She leaned across and put her hand on mine. “Malcolm,” she said, “we were good friends once, and I’ve sometimes thought I didn’t treat you very well.” I said something or other—I don’t know what. “But you’re still a young man, and it’s not too late now for you to marry some nice girl and be happy with her, as you used to want to be. There’s ever so many nice girls about, Malcolm. You mustn’t go and hurt all your old friends by getting down too low. I know what men are, of course … but don’t go down too far, Malcolm.” And she glanced across the room at Sixpence, sitting all alone.

I knew that Sixpence wasn’t happy there. It was not that she was unaccustomed to a good hotel, because she evidently was; she knew the ropes all right, but there was a bleak austerity about the place that might have daunted anyone. She was sitting rather stiffly on her chair, ill at ease and anxious in the menacing presence of the waiters. In the freezing cleanness of that room she looked a little shabby and a little over–dressed; the paint upon her face showed up most cruelly.

I smiled. “Looks a bit high and dry, doesn’t she?” I said cynically. I knew that I must get back to her; it was bad luck for her to be made to feel like that upon the first day of her holiday.

“Who is she, Malcolm?”

I glanced at Marion for a moment, thinking what a different life I should have had to lead if we had gone through with it. Some things cannot be explained; I knew that Marion would never understand me if I talked to her all night. I shrugged my shoulders. “One of my little friends,” I said “I picked her up in Leeds.”

She withdrew her hand. “You’ve changed a lot, Malcolm,” she said quietly.

I nodded. “I dare say. It’s probably as well we never married, Marion.”

She had nothing to say to that.

I ground the stub end of my cigarette down upon the tray. “Things change,” I said, “and people. And one gets to think about things differently. It’s been jolly seeing you again, Marion, but now I think I must get back to her.” I smiled. “I paid her ten pounds to come away with me, you see, and I must get my money’s worth.”

She sighed a little, and I left her to her life of freezing clean hotels, her two hygienic children and their nurse, and all the Best People that she knew, and I went back to Sixpence. “This room simply shatters me,” I said, and glanced around me with distaste. “It’s like a ruddy ice house.”

She rippled softly into laughter. “Oh, you are funny!” she said. “I mean, I’ve been feeling like that, too. It’s terribly grand, isn’t it?”

She had finished lunch while I had been talking to Marion. “Let’s get out of it,” I said.

She stared at me. “Don’t you want any more to eat? You haven’t had half enough, driving all that way.”

I smiled. “Don’t want any more,” I said. “The food would choke me. You want to trifle with lark’s tongues in aspic and talk about Marcel Proust when you lunch here.”

She stared at me. “Who was she?”

“I don’t know,” I replied. “That’s why we’re going.” And I sent the waiter for the bill.

We settled down again into the Bentley and went wandering south between the hills to Ludlow, running at an easy speed. All afternoon we ran southwards by the border, through Ludlow to Hereford and down to Ross. Then we cut across to Gloucester and down beside the Cotswolds, till finally we ran into Bristol in good time for tea.

I turned to Sixpence as we drove through the suburbs of the town. “I chose that place for lunch,” I said, “and it turned out to be a dud. You’d better have a shot this time, and choose where we have tea.”

I thought for a moment. “We’ll have to have supper on the road, I think. We’ll be a bit late getting in, and I haven’t told them we should want a meal. Would you like a meat tea and a light supper somewhere?”

She looked up at me doubtfully. “Would you like that? I mean, is that what you have?”

I laughed. “I had my way about lunch. You’ve got to choose where we have tea.”

She laughed with me. “Let’s just walk about a bit and see what the places are like. I mean, fancy asking for an egg to your tea in where we had lunch. Wouldn’t it be awful?” And so we slid into the centre of the town among the traffic.

We found a place to park the car and walked out into the streets, looking for our tea. In the end we found a place, a sort of teashop, not too pretentious; she paused outside and looked up at me doubtfully, and said: “Do you think this is nice?” So we went inside and ate a meal of tea and poached eggs and iced cakes. Sixpence finished up with a strawberry ice, but I couldn’t face that; at the end she sighed happily and said: “It is nice here, isn’t it?” I helped her on with her coat, and for that little service she turned to me impulsively and said: “You are kind!”

And then I went and spoilt it all. I don’t know now exactly how it came to happen; some tone or inflexion in my voice, I suppose, that brought her little castle tumbling down. She asked if we had time to walk up the street a little way to look at the shops, and so we strolled on slowly, pausing every now and then. First it was a leather shop that caught her eye, and she paused to admire the bags and dressing cases in the window. Next it was a window full of evening frocks; that held us for a long time, and I was told that she looked best in green. All the girls said so.

This shop–inspecting expedition, I could see, was going to cost me money. That put things on a different footing; to me it became a matter of business then, and I began calculating the chances dispassionately. My job was to get her safe to Newton Abbot and hand her over to the police for the identification of the lorry; I had sent a wire to Norman to say that I was bringing her down. While she was in my hands my business was to keep her quiet and amenable; what happened when I had delivered up the goods was no concern of mine. The next move was evidently that I should buy her something and I was quite prepared to play my part. What to buy I neither knew nor cared.

It was in this frame of mind that we came to the jewellers, and we stopped a long time there. First it was a pendant that attracted her, and then a brooch; in my preoccupation I was amused to study her and to notice that her taste was by no means bad. We stayed there so long that I became aware that it was here that I must do my stuff. I don’t suppose there was a thing in that window worth much more than twenty pounds.

It was a brooch, a single bar of platinum with an emerald in the middle, that she was admiring at the time. I smiled, thinking it was like giving toys to a child to make it be good. “You can have that, if you like,” I said. “Or any of these other things.”

As soon as I had spoken I knew that I had done it wrong. She stared up at me, wrinkling her brows. “Do you mean you’d give it me?” she demanded.

I didn’t quite know what to say to that. “If you’d like it,” I replied. “Either that or anything else in there that you’d like.”

She stood there staring up at me. “Do you mean I can have anything I like out of that window? Anything I like to ask you for?”

I nodded. “If you’d like anything there.”

There was a silence. She stood looking in at the window without speaking for a minute, and I knew that things had gone most desperately wrong. In an endeavour to retrieve the situation I said awkwardly: “Would you like to go inside and have a look round?”

She shook her head. “I don’t think I want anything now. They’re not very nice.”

I was humbled and amazed. We went on looking at shops in a desultory manner, but all her pleasure in the walk was gone. She seemed listless and depressed, and after a decent interval she suggested that perhaps it was time we got on the road again. So we went back to the car. By that time I knew what was wrong. I had hurt her very deeply by the way in which I had offered her the whole contents of the shop; I could imagine that in her parlance that was not the way a gentleman would give a present to his girl friend. The worst of it was that I could see no way in which to put things right.

We slid out of the town into the suburbs and up the hill upon the Axbridge road. It was a lovely evening on the road, but that didn’t do us any good. Before, she had been chattering to me all the way, pointing out things by the roadside and lighting cigarettes for me, but now she sat quiet by my side and even the automatic lighter failed to amuse. From time to time she said something with forced gaiety, but there was a constraint between us that the swift passing of the miles did nothing to remove.

We went down through Axbridge and across Sedgemoor, through Bridgwater to Taunton. With the coming of the evening we ran into Devonshire and down to Exeter. It was about half–past seven when we passed through that; I took the Dartmouth road. I was in my own country by this time. Chudleigh was my destination for this stage, and twenty minutes later we pulled up at the Running Hart for supper.

Try as I may, I cannot remember much about that meal. I suppose we ate in silence punctuated by little forced remarks; I know that nothing happened which would make the situation any easier. Only one thing I remember. They know me at the Running Hart, and they gave me to wait at table a boy that I know something of, whose uncle is a shipwright in my yard. This boy is a pretty good golfer in his leisure time; he got into the semi–final of the South Devon Championship that year. I think he must have told us about that as he served the meal, because I cannot think of any other way in which I should have known.

It was nearly dark when we had finished. We had a cup of coffee in the lounge; several times during that I felt that Sixpence wanted to say something, but it didn’t come. At last we went out to the car. I had turned her off the road into the stable yard, and there she was standing on the cobbles by the mountain block, gleaming a little and enormous in the dusk. Sixpence had followed me, a pace or so behind, but as I opened the door for her to get in she stopped motionless beside the car.

“Mr Stevenson,” she said, so low that I had to drop my head to catch her words. “Please, I don’t think I want to come on any further with you. I’m so dreadfully sorry….”

There was a bat wheeling and darting round the yard against a deep blue sky. I stood there staring absently into the dusk, at the dark shadows in the open stable doors, the tin advertisements of poultry food upon the russet walls, the haystack by the gate. This was the England that I knew; in coming down from Leeds I had come south from a foreign land, and brought with me a foreign girl.

I bent towards her. “It’s exactly as you like,” I said. “You needn’t come with me unless you want to, you know.” That wasn’t true, of course. Now that I had got her so far she would certainly complete her journey to identify the wreck at Newton Abbot, whether with me or with the police.

She hesitated, at a loss for words. “I think I’d better spend the night here,” she said at last, “by myself. And then I’d go up north again by train tomorrow.”

I nodded. “I’m so very sorry this has gone wrong,” I said quietly. “I mean that. If you could tell me what’s the matter—I’d do anything I can to help, you know. Don’t worry if you’d rather not.”

She looked up at me. “I feel so awfully mean telling you,” she muttered, “after all the trouble you’ve taken, and the things you’ve done, and everything. It’s just that I don’t want to go on with it….”

I smiled at her. “That’s quite all right,” I said. “You don’t want to worry about that.” I knew that sort of scene by heart; it happens to me every eighteen months.

She raised her eyes and looked me straight in the face. “I’m so dreadfully sorry, and I didn’t mean it to end like this when I came away with you—truly I didn’t. I suppose it’s that I’m not really the sort of girl for this. And you’re not the sort of man, either.”

I was staring into the dim expanses of the field beyond the gate; the bat was still sweeping and circling about the eaves. “Why do you say that?” I asked, without looking at her. “Why do you say I’m not the sort of man?”

She hesitated, and then said: “The way you were talking to the waiter….”

She came a little closer to me in the dusk. “I’d like you to know,” she said simply, “because you’ve been so kind, and perhaps you won’t think so bad of me. Lots of the girls go away for holidays with gentlemen and just don’t seem to mind, but I never did that. Only once, and I didn’t know about things then; I was seventeen, and I didn’t know. And that was ever so long ago—I’m quite old, you know.” She smiled up at me tremulously. “And then you came, and it was all so different, I’d never had a gentleman quite like you before, although I’ve met lots, you know, coming to dance. And then I couldn’t have my holiday, and I was sort of silly about that, although it doesn’t do to be silly about things, does it? And then you came and asked me to come away with you. And I thought it didn’t matter….”

It seemed to me that this young woman was labouring under a considerable misapprehension as to the nature of her holiday. I stood there resting one foot upon the running board of the Bentley and I was silent for a minute, considering the position. At last I said:

“You can go home if you like—you know that—and I’ll fix up a room for you here, and go away. But you’re quite wrong about me.”

She looked up at me. “I don’t understand.”

I dropped my foot down from the running board and stood erect. “I’m thirty–nine years old,” I said, “and I must be a damn fool, because although I’ve got plenty of money I’ve never taken a girl away the way you mean. Not even when I’ve had it chucked at my head. You were right when you said I’m not that sort of man, and I don’t take any credit for that, either, because it’s how you happen to be made.”

I paused. “You think that because I offered to buy you anything you wanted from that shop, that I was trying to buy you. Well, I wasn’t, as a matter of fact. I meant you to come down to my place for an ordinary holiday, like I told you.”

She stood there looking up at me. “I don’t understand,” she said again. “I’ve never met anyone like you a bit….”

I smiled at her. “We aren’t going on our honeymoon,” I said, “although I know it looks a bit like that. I meant it to be just an ordinary holiday for you—sort of staying with friends. Only there’s only me and the servants in the house.”

“You mean you just wanted me to come and keep you company, sort of?” She paused. “Not anything more than that?”

I nodded. “Nothing more than that.”

There was a little silence then, and then she said, half to herself: “Just because you were lonely, like, living alone.” I hadn’t anything to say to that.

She raised her face to mine. “I’d like to come on with you,” she said simply, “if you’ll let me now. I didn’t know it was like that. You must think me awful, though….”

It was very dark and shadowy in the yard. It seemed to me that I had slipped back fifteen years, that I was still a boy with all the glamour of a young man’s life in front of me, that I could mould my life to what I chose and make it good.

“My dear,” I said, “I think you’re simply sweet.”

In the dim light her upturned face was like a flower. “You’ve been so kind to me,” she murmured in the dusk. “I don’t know what to say.”

The bat was still wheeling and flickering above our heads against a deep blue sky, the poultry food advertisements had faded into dim shadows on the russet walls, the night was very still. She stood there very close to me, her face upturned to mine; we were more together then than we had ever been. With a little sigh she came into my arms and rubbed her face against my overcoat.

It was over seven years since I had kissed a girl.

After a little time we came unstuck, and got into the car. I swung her out of the stable yard on to the road, and then we sat quiet for a time in the gloom behind the headlights, very close together, talking in low tones. It is twenty miles from Chudleigh to my house. It seemed like two to me, that night.

We passed through Dartmouth and up the shoulder of the hill. At the top I swung the car in through the gates and up the drive, and we came to rest on the gravel sweep before the house, three hundred miles from Leeds. I switched off the engine, and the silence closed down on us, infinite, complete. We sat there for a moment silent in the dark; then I stirred, and we got out of the car.

The front door opened and Rogers was there with one of the maids; he came forward and busied himself with our luggage. I spoke a word or two to him; from the open door a stream of light poured out into the darkness where we stood. Then I turned to where the girl was standing by the car.

She came up to me: “Is this where you live?”

“That’s right,” I said. “Let’s go indoors.”

She hung back a little by the car. “It’s awfully big,” she breathed. “It’s like the pictures….” And then she said: “Whatever is that noise?”

I listened for a moment. I could hear nothing beyond the usual small noises of the night, the rustling of branches in the breeze, the low murmur from the beach. I laughed. “That’s the sea you hear,” I said. “On the rocks, just down below that lawn. You’ll see it from your window in the morning when you wake.”

For a little time we stood there listening, sniffing the sea air. “That’s it,” I said. “It’s when the wind’s in the south–east that it makes that noise. Blows straight in.”

“Oh——” she said. “It’s going to be lovely here.”

We went into the house. Mrs Rogers, my housekeeper, was in the hall; I noticed that she looked at her a little bit askance. I spoke a word or two to Mrs Rogers on the subject of spare rooms and light refreshments, and by the time I’d finished she had clearly understood that her position would be vacant if she gave me any nonsense of that sort. She went away then, and I had no further trouble with her in that way.

Both Sixpence and I were tired from the drive; there was a fire in the library, and we went in there. She was shy and very quiet, very observant of the house. She refused a drink, but jumped at the proposal of a cup of tea and a piece of cake before the fire; I poured myself out a whisky and put on a few records on the gramophone to allow her to keep quiet. Then we were ready for bed.

I took her up and showed her to her room. There was a bright fire burning in the grate and the room looked very comfortable; her things were all laid out. She hadn’t very much. I looked round and made sure that she had everything she wanted for the night—soap and towels and all the rest of it. I crossed with her to the window and drew back the curtain; two hundred feet below the moon cast dappled shadows on the water at the harbour mouth. “There’s the sea,” I said. “You’ll see it all when you wake up.”

We turned back into the room.

“What’s that door?” she asked.

I crossed the room and opened it, smiling a little; the light shone brightly on white tiles and silver pipes. “That’s your bathroom,” I replied. “Not my bedroom, as you might suppose.”

She rippled into laughter. “Oh, you are funny. I mean, I didn’t mean that when I asked you what the door was.” She sighed. “It’s all so lovely here I don’t know what to say.”

“Better say goodnight,” I remarked. “That’s a safe one, anyway.”

She came up to me. “Goodnight,” she said simply. “And thank you so much for the lovely day I’ve had.”

“Goodnight,” I said, and went down to the library again. There were one or two letters to be opened, and one or two instructions to be given to Rogers about matters of the house. And then I sat smoking for a long time, irresolute, staring into the fire. At last I reached out for the telephone and rang up Fedden at his house.

“Well,” I said, “I’ve got the girl down here. What do you want done with her?”

There was a moment’s pause. “One moment. Where is she? Where are you speaking from?”

“Speaking from my house,” I said. “You don’t want her tonight, do you? I’ve sent her up to bed.”

“I can’t do anything with her tonight,” he replied. “We’ll examine her in the morning. You know Norman’s down here? He came down this afternoon. About this girl—has she made any statement to you?”

“None at all. I haven’t tried for one. I brought her down here because I thought she could identify the lorry.”

He paused. “I don’t understand. How did you get her to come down here, then?”

“Personal charm,” I said laconically.

“Oh….” There was a little silence then, because Fedden is a better sort than I am. “Then she doesn’t know anything at all about this matter—why you’ve brought her down?”

“Nothing whatsoever,” I replied. “Still, I’ve got her here. What do you want me to do with her?”

He considered for a moment. “Bring her to Newton Abbot police station at half–past ten tomorrow morning,” he said at last. “I’m meeting Norman there at ten. In all probability he’ll show her the lorry there.”

“All right. Are you any good at scenes?”

“Did you say scenes?”

“Yes, scenes. You’d better come prepared for one, because we’re pretty sure to have it.”

“Oh….”

“One thing more,” I said. “I take it that my responsibility ends tomorrow, when I hand her over to you. I’ll arrange to have her clothes packed up and sent along to you later in the day. The position is that I deliver her to you at Newton Abbot, and you take charge of her from then onwards.”

He hesitated. “If you like. I don’t see that we can ask you to do anything further in the matter after that.”

“That’s all I wanted to be sure about,” I said. “Goodnight.”

I put up the receiver and moved the decanter over to a table by my chair. The fire was dying in the grate; I threw on more coal and beat it savagely into a blaze.

I sat there till the room grew cold and dark. Then I went up to bed.

Chapter 6

I can’t have got much sleep that night, because I was awake at dawn. That was about four o’clock, I should suppose; it must have been about the second or third of June. I lay and watched the light growing in the room till I could see from the glow that there was sunlight out of doors, and a clear sky and an easterly wind for settled weather.

It was no good lying in bed; I gave up the attempt to sleep, got up, and had a bath. Then I went downstairs in my dressing gown and pyjamas and wandered absently about the house a bit; my chair and glass were as I had left them in the library an hour or two before. I went through into the model room and drew the blinds. The morning sun streamed through into the room and I stood there idly for a little time, studying the hull shapes on my drawing board. At that time I was working on the design of the small cruising yacht that I laid down last month when I came back to Dartmouth; I think she will turn out a pretty little craft, embodying all that I have ever learnt about the game.[1] I stood there studying the lines till I became absorbed, moved T–square and curves, and stood there working at the hull until I heard the servants moving round the house.

I went upstairs to shave and dress, and when I came down again Sixpence was before me. I came down into the hall treading quietly on the thick carpet of the stairs, and stood there for a moment sorting through my letters. Then I looked up and through the open door of the library I saw her standing at the entrance to the model room. She had not heard me in the hall.

I watched her for a minute. She stood there very quiet, staring about her, taking it all in. She was dressed in the same grey costume that she had worn the previous day and had taken the same pains over her face; her thick black hair was coiled about her ears. I watched her as she moved slowly forward into the model room, treading very softly as though she was uncertain if she ought to be there at all. She passed into the sunlight by the window; deep colours showed up in the folds of her hair and warm tints on her neck below the powder line; she moved with a quiet grace that was, perhaps, in part an attribute of her profession. She stood there for a time by the window in the sun, looking about her at the models, careful not to touch the cases as she moved. Presently she slipped over to my drawing board and paused for a long time over that, uncomprehending.

I smiled, and went up a few steps of the stairs, and came down upon the resonant woodwork at the side. I turned into the library and found her there. “Morning,” I said; “did you sleep well?”

She nodded. “Lovely,” she said. And then she said: “It is a lovely house. I think it’s just a dream.”

I smiled, and moved forward to the door. “This is the model room,” I said. “Where I do my work—some of it. What I don’t do down at the office I do here.” I stared around. “There’s not much here but ships.”

She said: “The maid told me, when she came to wake me up. Oh, and I mean—I’ve been calling you all wrong. You must think me awful! But you never told me different. I’ve been calling you Mr Stevenson all the time.”

I laughed. “That’s what I ought to be called. It’s only because I have to do with ships that they call me Commander. I was only in the Navy in the war.”

She looked up at me uncertainly. “Oh … I didn’t know.” And then she said: “She said you were up working, ever so early. Didn’t you sleep properly? I slept lovely after all that driving.”

“You don’t sleep so much as you get older,” I replied. “I often get up early in the summer.”

This was an opening she knew. “Oh, you are funny,” she replied. “You aren’t old.”

I grinned at her. “I’ve got enough grey hair, anyway,” I said.

She looked around, and sighed. “I’d sleep for ever in a lovely house like this,” she said.

We went through into the dining–room for breakfast. I saw her glance around as she sat down, a swift circular glance that seemed to take in everything from the silver on the table to the portraits of my family upon the walls. “I’ve got to go over to Newton Abbot this morning,” I remarked as we sat down. “Would you like to come too?” I paused. “I’m running over in the car.”

She looked at me doubtfully. “Are you sure I wouldn’t be in the way? I mean, it’s all so lovely here I don’t want you to bother.”

I smiled, a little bitterly: “You needn’t worry about that. I’d like it if you’d come to keep me company.”

She smiled at me. “It would be lovely. I do like driving in your car. It is a nice one, isn’t it?”

“It goes all right,” I said, and so we got on with the meal. I had grown queerly callous by that time and could listen quite unmoved while she chatted to me about holidays that she had taken with her brother, years before, holidays at Colwyn Bay and Southport. I listened with a detached, critical interest while she spoke of him, trying to make out from her account what sort of man this brother of hers was. She had a great regard for him. To her he was everything that was fine and manly and courageous; it was the idolism of a child. I wondered what the man was really like.

He was three years older than her. That put him at about twenty–eight years old, I thought.

We left the house soon after breakfast; that was a rotten drive. I was silent and preoccupied, and after a little time Sixpence grew quiet and didn’t worry me. I noticed that at the time, and I remembered wondering if she had smelt a rat. In any case, there was nothing she could do about it now; my business was so nearly over.

It was in that frame of mind that we drove into Newton Abbot and drew up before the police station, exactly at the time agreed upon. The town was all spattered with election posters. I remember that because it was the first time I had seen the things that year. It must have been about six weeks before the poll.

As the car came to a standstill, I said: “You’d better come inside with me. I shan’t be long.” She looked a little startled, but I turned away and she followed me in through the door and into the same room where I had been shown the gun. Norman and Fedden were waiting for us there.

I spoke first: “This is Miss Gordon, who’s come down with me,” I said. “Major Norman—Colonel Fedden.”

They bowed to her, and she murmured something that I couldn’t catch. I didn’t care to look at her.

“We have the lorry outside, in the yard,” said Norman. “I think perhaps we’d better go and see that first.” He turned to the girl. “Will you come, too, Miss Gordon?” he said pleasantly.

She smiled at him, and we went through the door and out into the yard. There was a mass of wreckage beneath a tarpaulin in a corner of the wall; two constables were uncovering it as we went out.

Norman turned to the girl, and when he spoke his voice was very grave. “Miss Gordon,” he said quietly. “I think you told Commander Stevenson that your brother was the owner of a motor–lorry—a thirty–hundredweight Dennis lorry.” He paused. “I am very sorry to say that we have had an accident down here recently—rather a bad accident. Do you think you would know your brother’s lorry again?”

She stared at him, wide eyed. “I don’t quite understand.” And then she said quickly: “Do you mean something’s happened to Billy?”

His manner was perfect. “Please, Miss Gordon,” he said, “there’s nothing to distress yourself about at the moment. I want you just to walk round this lorry with me, and see if you can see anything on it that you can identify. That’s all.”

The wreckage was completely uncovered by this time. It lay there on the asphalt of the yard, broken and twisted and already red with rust. I was standing with Fedden a little way apart. He looked at me awkwardly, and said in a low tone:

“Norman is very experienced in dealing with these cases. You can safely leave her in his hands, if you’d rather slip away now.”

I glanced at him sharply. “I’d rather stay,” I said. “I want to see how this is done.”

He made no answer, but stood there fidgeting a little—a decent man in an impossible position. Norman had moved closer to the lorry with the girl, and was talking to her in a very gentle tone. She had forgotten we were there, I think.

“It caught on fire in the middle of the night,” he was saying, “on the road, not very far from here. There was nobody there at the time, and when help came it was burning so fiercely that no one could get near it to do anything. Everything in it was destroyed—we don’t even know what it was loaded with. As you can see, it was completely burnt out….” He hesitated. “And the driver….” He stopped.

She was staring at him, dumb with horror. “Please … ” she whispered in the end. “Please tell me. What happened to the driver?”

He paused for a moment, as if he didn’t quite know what to say. “I am afraid, Miss Gordon,” he said very gently, “we don’t quite know what happened to the driver. It was all so utterly burnt up, you see.”

It was a moment before she realised what he meant; then for a minute I thought she was going to break down. But she had guts, that girl, and all that happened was that she began fumbling at the catch of her handbag, mechanically trying to open it. It would not come undone and she stood there fumbling at it desperately, her head bent down. I don’t know what it was she wanted out of it, perhaps a handkerchief.

“Come,” said Norman, “there’s nothing to distress yourself about. We don’t know that this is your brother’s lorry. Perhaps it may not be.”

She swallowed once or twice. “I—I should know Billy’s lorry,” she said at last. “I think so.” She looked up at him pitifully. “It has horseshoes on it.”

He spoke to her very gently, immensely kind. “Then let’s just have a look at it together,” he suggested. “Two heads are better than one, aren’t they? And you can tell me if you see anything you recognise.”

I stood there looking on at this dumbfounded, amazed at the cleverness of the man. He had said nothing that was not true. It was true that the lorry had been burning fiercely when it was discovered, true that he knew nothing of the driver’s fate. I could see that he would get the whole of the evidence he wanted without the slightest difficulty; if she had anything damaging to tell she could commit her brother up to the hilt without ever knowing she had injured him. The whole of her examination was being cast into the form of an inquiry into the supposed death of her brother, and she would tell everything she knew.

A more educated, more sophisticated girl might possibly have broken out of the snare that he had made for her by puzzling over the circumstances that had brought her to that yard; she might have smelt a rat. I could see that Norman had nothing to fear from that. The girl was very nearly in tears, hanging back a little from the wreckage in the corner that he was trying to get her to inspect.

“Come, Miss Gordon,” he said, “we must just have a look at it, you know.” There was an air of gentle authority in his voice which made her come to him at once. Together they walked slowly up the length of that tangled, rusty mass of iron.

They moved round to the front. I saw her stop, I saw the muscles of her face working. I saw her catch her breath as she pointed to something on the ruins of the radiator. I couldn’t see what it was from where I was standing. I saw Norman bend down to her, infinitely solicitous.

“Is that your brother’s?” he asked gently.

She nodded once or twice, dumbly. “It was a little one—just like that. He—he said it was a donkey’s…. There was a big one on the back.”

Norman inclined his head. “We found a big one on the road, underneath,” he said quietly. “It must have been nailed on to some wooden part.”

There was an infinite silence in the yard.

“Come,” said Norman, “just one more look, and then we’ll go indoors. I want you to tell me if there’s anything else that you can recognise. There might still be some mistake, you know.”

They walked together slowly down the other side. The steering column was bent and twisted down; the thin bare core of the wheel stood up forlornly. Below the wheel a little clip was mounted carrying a ring, clumsy, amateurish fitting at the best. She laid her hand on this.

“He used to put his pipe in that,” she said in a low tone. “He put it on himself, because he told me.” She turned to him with a trembling lip. “Please—mayn’t we go indoors now?”

“I think we may, Miss Gordon,” he said kindly. “There’s nothing more that we can do out here.” He hesitated for a moment, and then said: “I am so very, very sorry.”

She made no reply to that; I don’t think she was capable of saying anything. She walked across the yard with him towards the door we had come out of; Fedden and I followed them a few paces behind. It seemed to me that the art of criminal investigation had advanced a step or two since Sherlock Holmes.

At the door Fedden made another effort to get rid of me. “There’s nothing more for you to stay for, if you’d like to get away,” he said. “We can take care of her now, and send her back up north.”

I gave him a grim stare. “I should prefer to stay,” I said shortly. “I want to see what fancy games you gentlemen are going to play with her.” He winced at that, as I had meant he should.

He said something or other, but I brushed past him and followed Norman into the office. He was already seated at the table there, the girl opposite him. He gave me a sharp glance as I came in, which I ignored; I knew that he could do nothing to eliminate me without arousing her suspicions. I took up a stand on the far side of the room, half turned away from them, looking out of the window. Fedden came in and closed the door, and stood by me. At a corner table there was a sergeant taking notes, armed with a notebook and pencil.

“Now, Miss Gordon,” Norman was saying, “Just one or two questions that we have to ask, about this accident. I am sure you won’t mind.”

She looked up at him dumbly.

“First of all, what was your brother’s name?”

She answered in a low voice: “William Hartop Gordon.”

“And his age?”

“He was thirty last October.” So she was older than I thought.

“Where did he live?”

“It was somewhere in Birmingham, but I don’t know the address. He used to be in Wolverhampton, up till about a year ago.”

“Was he a married man?”

She shook her head without speaking.

“Do you remember where he lived in Wolverhampton?”

“He was in lodgings. Twenty–nine Elmer’s Crescent was the address.”

Norman smiled at her kindly. “Just one or two more questions, Miss Gordon.” He paused. “When did you see your brother last?”

She swallowed. “In Leeds. I think it was about a month ago. You see, he came and booked me out.”

“I see,” said Norman; “and you went out with him. Did you go in his lorry?”

She tried to speak, and failed. She shook her head, and then she said, a little piteously: “Please, do you think I might have a glass of water?”

The sergeant rose, lumbering from his table, and went out of the room; he returned in a minute with a dripping cup. She took it from him gratefully and drank; Norman sat patiently till she had finished.

“That’s better,” he said kindly. “Now, Miss Gordon did your brother work for anybody? or was this lorry his own property?”

She said: “I think it was his own.”

“I see.” He was silent for a minute, and then: “Did he ever tell you what work he used to do, or who he used to work for? I mean, whose loads he used to carry in the lorry?”

She said: “Oh, yes.” I swung round sharply by the window, and she stopped and looked at me.

“That’s enough of this damn foolery,” I said harshly.

There was a momentary silence. I stood there staring down at Norman at the table, watching the deep colour mounting in his face. He turned and beckoned to the sergeant, who got up and came towards me. “I’ll see you about that afterwards, Commander Stevenson,” he said easily. “In the meantime, perhaps you wouldn’t mind waiting outside?”

The sergeant opened the door for me.

I laughed shortly. “If you like,” I said. “In that case I shall go straight up to town. I can get a question asked about this matter in the House tonight.”

Fedden stirred uneasily beside me, and I swung round viciously on him. “Yes, by Christ,” I said, “and you’ll be in it, too. Chief Constable of the County!” And I laughed again.

“Don’t be a fool, Stevenson,” he retorted, not unkindly. “You must go home and leave this thing to us.”

“I’m damned if I do,” I said.

The girl sat staring at us, red eyed and uncomprehending, gripping a little wad of handkerchief in her lap. Norman got up from the table. “I think it would be better for us to talk this over outside,” he said smoothly. “In consideration for Miss Gordon.”

“I don’t,” I said curtly.

I crossed the room to where the girl was sitting by the table. “You’d better come along with me,” I said. “We’re going home.”

“Sit down!” said Norman sharply. She collapsed into her chair again, and I saw a tear fall down her cheek. He turned on me, red with anger. “As for you, sir, you must get out of this room. Go to town or go to hell for all I care. Get out!”

I put one foot up on to a chair and stared at him; there was an awkward silence after that outburst. “I’m a friend of Miss Gordon’s,” I said at last. “I want this inquiry adjourned till she has had an opportunity to consult her solicitor.”

Fedden broke in. “Don’t talk such nonsense,” he said irritably. “The girl hasn’t got a solicitor.”

I raised my eyebrows. “Louden, Jenkinson and Priestley are acting for her,” I replied. “Either Jenkinson or his junior will be here tonight.”

Norman broke in: “That’s a London firm.”

“Don’t be a damn fool,” I said sourly. “Do you think I put my business with a hedge solicitor?”

There was a momentary silence, and I followed up: “I would have you understand that I am making formal application for an adjournment of this inquiry, in order that Miss Gordon may take legal advice. You clearly understand that, Major Norman?—and Colonel Fedden?” I swung round on the sergeant. “You too. You may have to give evidence on this in Court. You understand what I want?”

“That’s enough,” said Norman sharply. “He understands well enough.”

The girl stirred beside me as if she wanted to say something, but I silenced her with a motion. “Look here,” I said to Norman, “you want to get to the bottom of this thing; so do I. I want to know who cracked me on the head that night. But I’ll be no party to a trick like this.”

Fedden stirred. “Have you any alternative procedure to suggest?” he asked coldly.

I eyed him for a moment. “None at all. My solicitor deals with legal—and illegal—matters of this sort for me. I think you will find that he is able to suggest some alternative procedure to this sort of thing.” I paused. “I imagine that he will advise Miss Gordon to make a statement to you, under his guidance.”

Norman interposed: “She can make a statement now. This matter is urgent.” He swung round on me. “You’re playing the fool with matters you don’t understand. How do you know what this delay may mean?”

I shrugged my shoulders. “You’ll have to take your chance of that. You’ve waited four days for me to bring her here, and you can wait a fifth for her solicitor.” I considered for a moment. “I’ll say this for her: Miss Gordon will give you a statement of some sort tomorrow afternoon.”

“Tomorrow morning,” he said.

I shook my head. “It can’t be done. Jenkinson can’t get here till late, and Miss Gordon won’t be fit to work with him tonight. Tomorrow afternoon.”

He turned on his heel and swung over to the door. “You’d better see your friend off the premises,” he said bitterly to Fedden, and then he was gone. Fedden said something or other, but I ignored him and turned to where the girl was sitting by the table. She turned a tear–streaked face to me.

“Please, Mr Stevenson,” she said—“oh, I mean, Commander Stevenson—I’m sorry, I didn’t mean—” She abandoned that sentence and started again. “I don’t quite understand what’s been happening,” she said, a little pitifully.

I smiled. “I know you don’t,” I said. “I’ll tell you about it when we get home. We’ll get along now and”—I searched my brain for words of feminine comfort—“you can have a cup of tea and a bit of cake, and lie down for a bit if you want to. Come on.” I stared around. “Got all your things?”

She got up and picked her bag up from the table. “There’s one thing you may as well know right away,” I said. “Your brother’s all right. He wasn’t in that lorry when it got burnt up.”

She stared at me. “Did he go to Hammersmith?” Fedden was there, all ears, and I said hurriedly: “That’s enough about that.”

I spoke sharply, I suppose, because she started crying in real earnest then. I was too much occupied in getting her out of the building before she put her foot in it again to pay much heed to that. I got her out and into the Bentley in double quick time, and she sat there crying by my side as we slid out of the town. A policeman on point duty looked curiously at us as we swept past, and I wondered if he thought I was abducting her. If I were, I reflected, it was from the police.

She dried up after a mile or two, but all that drive we never spoke a word. I thought it best to leave her to herself, and so we went along in silence all the way. We got back to the house at about half–past twelve. I left the car standing on the drive and took her through into the library, sat her down in a chair, reached out for the telephone and put in a trunk call to Jenkinson. Then I turned to her.

“Now,” I said, “what are you going to have? Cup of tea? Lunch will be ready in about three–quarters of an hour.”

She shook her head miserably. “Please, I don’t want anything.”

I stood there looking down at her, and thought that I had never seen a girl less likely to enjoy her lunch than this one. I rang the bell, and told Rogers to get her a cup of Bovril and some toast. It was the best thing I could think of. “You needn’t have it if you don’t want it when it comes,” I said. “You can just sniff at it then go upstairs and lie down if you want to.”

She smiled up at me weakly. “You’re ever so kind to me.” And then she said: “I don’t understand a bit what happened over there.”

“No,” I said, “I don’t suppose you do.” I paused for a minute, and lit a cigarette. “It’s a very long story and I’m not going to tell you now—not all of it. I’ll tell you after dinner tonight, when you’ve had a rest. But the bit you want to know now is this.”

I paused, and looked at her reflectively. “Those men over there were police officers,” I said. “Did you know that?”

She shook her head. “I didn’t know who they were.”

“Well,” I said, “you know now. They were playing a trick on you. They wanted to find out something about your brother.”

She stared at me, her brows wrinkled in perplexity. “They said he’d had an accident.”

I shook my head. “Not him. He wasn’t in that lorry when it got burnt up—he’s very much alive somewhere. They just told you that for a trick, so that you would tell them everything you knew about him. You would have done, wouldn’t you?”

She stared at me, wide eyed. “Of course I would.” And then she said: “What did they want to know about him for? Has he done anything wrong?”

I shook my head. “I’ll tell you this evening,” I replied. “It’s nothing very bad. He’s got himself mixed up in a much bigger business. But you don’t want to worry about that. It’s going to be all right.”

Her Bovril came then, and my trunk call. I picked up the telephone and spoke to Jenkinson in London.

“Look here,” I said, “I’ve got myself into a bit of a mess down here, I’m afraid, with the police. Yes; no, not a motoring offence—something rather more serious than that. I’ve got a CID man from Scotland Yard down here sitting on my doorstep waiting for a statement. Yes. Do you think you could slip down tonight? One of your juniors would do if you can’t, but I’d very much rather you came if you can, old boy. If it’s not terribly inconvenient. That’s really very decent of you. Well, you can catch the 5.30—gets to Exeter at 8.45. That’s the easiest way. Tonight, that is. Yes I’ll have the car there, at Exeter, at 8.45. Right you are. See you then. Goodbye.”

I hung up the receiver. “That’s your solicitor,” I said. “He’s coming down tonight.”

She wrinkled her brows. “Is that what you were speaking about over there?” she asked. “From London?”

“That’s right,” I said.

“Oh—” And then she said: “Please, I don’t think you quite understand—” She came to an end there, and I was puzzled; I couldn’t make out what she was driving at.

“Couldn’t I have somebody from here?”

I stared at her. “But this is one of the best men in the country—much better than anyone in a little town like this. He’ll have these policemen absolutely taped. He handles all my work.”

“I know—” She hesitated. “But coming all down from London like that. You see, I haven’t got very much money.” She looked up at me appealingly. “You do understand, don’t you?”

I was silent for a minute. When I spoke, I said: “My dear, he’s coming down for me. I didn’t mean it to cost you anything at all.”

She was troubled. “I don’t know what to say. It’s bound to cost a terrible lot, coming all that way.”

I smiled, a little ironically. “Not more than I can afford,” I said. She had finished her toast and Bovril. “Now look here, you’d better go upstairs and tidy yourself. You’d like some lunch, wouldn’t you?”

She shook her head.

“All right,” I said. “Go and lie down for a bit, or have a bath, or anything you like.” She smiled. “I’ve got to go down to my office after lunch, but I’ll be back about half–past four and we’ll have tea in here. In the meantime, you can explore the place. You can go anywhere you like, you know,” and I told her roughly the boundaries of my land. “Only don’t go bathing till I show you where to go. The tide runs out a bit fast round this point.”

She nodded obediently, and went upstairs. I went in and ate my lunch alone, and then took the car and went down to the yard. I spent the afternoon with Tillotson in the office, getting the hang of what had happened in my absence in the north. I had a ketch docking for a refit that day on the evening flood, the Sweet Anna, and I should have stayed to see her in. I usually do. But that afternoon I broke my rule and left the ship to Tillotson, and I went back to Sixpence in my house.

I found her in the model room when I got back. I saw her as I passed into the hall. She was sitting quietly on the window–seat gazing out through the open window over the sunlit garden to the deep blue sea. I don’t know what I had expected to find her doing, but I was surprised. She seemed to be doing nothing at all but sit there looking out over the harbour mouth. In an idle moment I might have sat like that myself.

She got up when I came in. “I’ve been looking at the little ships,” she told me. “They are lovely, aren’t they?”

I turned with her and looked at them. This room is a hobby for me, a room of reminiscences. One or two of the models are historical, the caravel and the fifteenth–century pinnace, but most of them are little vessels of my own, ships that I have owned or sailed in in my time, that I keep for remembrance and as pointers of experience. At the moment there are fourteen in the little fleet; all sail except the trawler, Martin Dodd.

Rogers brought tea to us in there and I moved about the room with Mollie, bread and butter in hand, talking to her about my little ships. She was interested and asked a lot of questions, and so we went round the room till finally we brought up at the Jane Ellen.

Sometimes I have thought that it would be better if I didn’t keep that model, and I have considered sending it to some museum. But there it is still, and she paused beside it. “What are those things on the deck?” she asked. “Are they guns?”

I nodded. “Those three are guns, and those two there are depth–charge throwers. That’s a vessel I was in in the war.”

She looked up at me, puzzled. I noticed that she had done something to her eyelashes. They were no longer waxed together in little groups, but lay long and soft upon her cheek. I wondered if that was because she had been crying, that they had come unstuck. “But it’s a sailing ship,” she said.

“Yes,” I said, “we used them in the war a bit.” I paused. “I wasn’t in her very long.”

I turned away and went back to the tea, and asked how she had spent the afternoon. She said, a little diffidently, that she hadn’t been outside—“it was all so lovely.” I took her out on to the terrace and showed her the lie of the hills and of the sea, and then we went down into the garden in the sun.

We spent all evening strolling round the place. Counting the Melcrose land I have about three hundred acres now but most of this is waste stuff—cliff and bracken. In the made gardens I found that she knew quite a lot about flowers and shrubs—rather more than I do, in fact. She had had a little garden of her own in Preston when she was living at home as a child. I took her through the hot houses, but I don’t think she cared much for those; she peered uncomprehendingly into the empty stalls of the stables. She was delighted with the fuzzy.

We call it the fuzzy, but I don’t know if that’s the proper name for it. It’s the coppice that fills the little ravine that runs down to my bathing beach. A stream runs down the middle of it in little waterfalls and it’s a great place for wild flowers—bluebells and primroses, and all that sort of thing. The path goes winding down the middle of it, and now and then as you go down to the beach you get a good view of the sea at the entrance. There is a beach at one of the corners, and we paused by that.

In the Range Sweet Anna lay at anchor, waiting for the ebb to slacken before going in. The wind was light, and she lay at anchor with both main and mizzen set, and swaying gently in the roll. As we watched the main came slowly down in great folds upon the deck; I stood and watched the hands gathering it up.

Mollie stirred beside me. “What’s that ship?” she asked. “Doesn’t she look lovely there?”

They were lashing the gaff down on the boom. “All ships are lovely,” I said, without taking my eyes from her. “That’s one of mine.”

“Oh—” she said. And then she said: “What’s she doing out there?”

I glanced down at her. “Waiting for the tug,” I said. “It should be here any minute now. We’ll wait and see.”

We sat down on the beach in the sun. “She’s a cargo ship, isn’t she?” she asked. “Goods, and that?”

I nodded. “She hasn’t got anything in her now. She’s just come up from Falmouth in ballast. She’s come in to refit.”

The Trojan came bustling into sight down the harbour, shoving a bow wave away from her broad bows. I saw her with pleasure as I always do; that tug is one of my extravagances. I bought her two years ago after a quarrel with the harbour tug–master and, buying a tug, I saw that I got a good one. Twin screw, driven by a couple of heavy oil engines, each of about three hundred horsepower, she’s a good seaworthy rough–weather boat; I’d rather go to sea in her than in our motor lifeboat any day. For my work, of course, she is too good. Too powerful, and more expensive than she need have been. That’s probably why I’m fond of her.

She ranged up alongside Sweet Anna in the calm sea, and they began to manhandle a hawser to her. Mollie turned to me. “What’s that they’re doing now?” she asked.

“Passing the tow rope.” I saw them man the windlass, and across the harbour mouth I heard the clanking of the pawls and the groaning of the chain. “They’re getting up anchor now.”

They broke it out and we watched the Trojan forge ahead, watched the foam gathering at her stem as she put on power, watched Sweet Anna stir and move ahead. They catted her anchor as she went, and we sat there watching tug and vessel till they passed from sight behind the point.

“Oh … ” said Mollie. “Was she really yours?”

I smiled. “She was. We’ll go and have a look at her tomorrow, if you like.”

In the evening everything was very gold and blue. “Oh,” she said, “it must be lovely to have ships like that.”

We went on down to the beach; there was a great calm over everything that night, and a faint easterly wind. I showed her the little hut that she could bathe from when she liked, and showed her the current running past the Checkstone buoy. “We’ll come down and bathe tomorrow, if it’s fine,” I said. “I don’t know if we’ll get Jenkinson to come in.”

We walked slowly back up through the wood towards the house. In the fuzzy there were thrushes calling in the evening, and high above our heads the seagulls swept along the cliff against a deep blue sky. We went up through the garden to the house, and stopped on the terrace to pick a few roses for her room.

It was getting on for dinnertime when we went in. She paused for a moment at the window leading into the library and turned to me. “It has been lovely going round like this, just sort of quietly,” she said. She stood looking out over the harbour mouth. “I do think it’s beautiful here.”

I turned into the house. “Let’s get a vase to put these roses in.”

She went and fetched one from her room, and I stood by the window and watched her while she pottered about arranging the flowers, clipping the stalks and talking about little trivial things. I could have given her nothing that pleased her more at the moment than those flowers for her bedroom, flowers that she had picked herself. I stood there listening to her talk and wondering, a little grimly, if I should ever learn to please a girl except by accident. It was time to dress for dinner, then, and she carried them carefully upstairs with her, and made me come into her room to see how nice they looked.

I didn’t stay there long. She had filled that bedroom with her personality; in some subtle way it had become peculiarly her own. I left her there and went on to my own room to dress. I must have taken rather longer than usual that night because she was down first; I found her in the hall examining the player–piano there.

I spoke a word or two to her, and she looked up at me. “Do you think I might play on it sometimes?” She looked doubtful. “I mean, when you’re at the office, or like that.”

I smiled. “Play on it any time you like,” I said. “I’ll show you where the rolls are kept.”

She followed me to the cupboard. “I didn’t mean that way,” she murmured. “I mean really play it. It does play properly as well, doesn’t it?”

I turned to her in surprise. “Oh, yes. Do you play much?”

She shook her head. “I never had more than a few lessons. But I do love a piano.”

She dropped her hands on to the keys and touched a chord. “Carry on,” I said.

She moved away hurriedly. “Oh, I couldn’t now. I don’t know very many pieces.”

She was always giving me little surprises of that sort. We went into dinner. She was wearing a dark blue dancing dress with a silver bodice; she had made herself look very pretty in it and I told her so. That set her smiling, and we dined merrily that night. I offered her Pommard, Barsac, or Château Yquem to drink, and found to my surprise that she knew something about wines. She said: “Could I have Barsac? I do like that. It’s a sort of sweet, like lemonade, isn’t it?” And so we had the Barsac that night.

Later we retired to sit in opposite corners of the chesterfield in the library, full of Barsac and roast duck and caramel pudding, and when Rogers had served our coffee and departed I told her everything I knew about her business. I told her how I had blundered into the affair when I had been as drunk as a lord, and how I had got what I deserved. And then I went on and told her the whole thing, how she had given me a cross bearing on the matter on that first night in the Palais by speaking of her brother and his lorry; I told her about Stenning and his tale of Rotterdam. Then I told her about the gun that Fedden had showed me, and how I had been with him to Scotland Yard. I didn’t hide anything from her; I told her how I had been sent to Leeds to get more information out of her, and how I had brought her down with me under false pretences to comfort her with the lorry.

She listened to me for the most part in silence, now and again asking trivial little questions. I am not sure that she ever really understood the inwardness of the affair. Finally I came to the incidents of the morning, and explained to her how she had been tricked into giving evidence about her brother.

I came to an end, and we sat for a little time in silence; she didn’t seem to have anything much to say about it all. “I’m not very proud of my part in this affair,” I said at last.

She stared at me helplessly. “I don’t know what to say. You didn’t do anything wrong. Lots of gentlemen could have been terribly nasty, but you weren’t.”

I smiled; her mind, I thought, was running in a groove. “In any case,” I said, “you needn’t worry much about this thing. Jenkinson’s a good man. I think you’ll find that Billy will come out of it all right.”

She didn’t seem to be much interested in him. Perhaps she had confidence in his ability to get himself out of any scrape he got himself into. “I don’t understand,” she said at last. “If you were on their side, why did you upset everything this morning like you did? They were terribly angry with you, weren’t they?”

I smiled, a little grimly. “I don’t know. Yes, I suppose they were.”

She wrinkled her brows. “I don’t see why you went against them like that.”

I was silent for a minute. “You can’t stand by and see a trick like that go on,” I said at last. “You might with a stranger, but not with somebody you know.”

She stared across at me with wonder in her eyes. “Oh,” she said softly. “You mean you did all that for me….”

There was a long silence after she said that. Presently she leaned across to me. “Please,” she said simply, “I think I’d like to go to bed now, if I may. I’m so tired. You said it would be all right if I saw the lawyer in the morning, didn’t you?”

And so she went, and I was left to wait for Jenkinson alone.

[1] This vessel was on the stocks at the decease of her designer. She was purchased and completed by Mr L. A. Stone of Salcombe, who christened her Mazurka III. — ed.

Chapter 8

That evening we went up to Thompson’s field and sat and waited for the aeroplane. Mollie had gone up to her room directly after lunch, and had come down in half an hour to find me working in the model room. She had changed into a jumper and an old brown skirt, and she had come to ask me if she would do. “I haven’t put hardly any powder on, or anything,” she informed me. “Do you think I’ll be all right like this for Lady Stenning?”

Her mind was still running on Joan. I laid my set–square down and grinned at her. “You’re quite all right,” I replied. “Looking very nice. You don’t want a lot of powder and stuff in those sort of clothes. It doesn’t go, does it?”

She smiled, and looked up at me. “You don’t like a lot of that, do you?” she inquired. “It’s funny how people are about that. Lots of the gentlemen just don’t care about taking you out unless you’ve got a lot on.”

She glanced down at her shoes; they were black, high heeled, and ornamental. “I didn’t bring my other pair of walking shoes down with me,” she said ruefully. “I thought they’d be too old for me to bring here. Does it matter?”

I laughed. “Not a hoot. But would you like to get a pair of country shoes? We’ll slip down in the car, if you like.”

She said: “I’d love it, ever so. But not now—when you’ve finished working.” And she indicated the drawing board.

“Playing,” I said, “up here. I do my work down at the office.”

“What is it?” she inquired.

I moved aside the T–square for her to examine the drawing. “It’s a ship,” I said. “The hull layout of a little yacht I want to build.”

She stared at it, uncomprehending. “You do love ships,” she said at last. “I wish I knew about them more.”

And so we left the house and went down to the town at gossip time, and drew the Bentley up before the local shoe emporium to provide fresh matter for discussion at the local tea tables. I knew all that before we went, of course, but Mollie came back in new brown brogues with tasselled laces and was happy for the afternoon.

They say that a man has licence to take off whatever clothes he puts on to a girl. I thought that I might take that risk, with shoes.

We sat on the gate to Thompson’s field for half an hour and waited for the aeroplane. We heard it first, and then we saw it in the sky, a speck above Kingswear. We watched it closer till the engine was shut off above the harbour, and the Moth came in on a wide gliding turn, side–slipped down across the hedge, and ran gently to rest in the middle of the field. Stenning swung her round and taxied in towards us; Mollie turned to me: “Wasn’t it pretty the way it did that?”

“He’s not got much to learn about an aeroplane,” I said.

Joan waved a hand from the front cockpit as they drew abreast of us; I got on to the wing tip and guided the machine towards the barn. Stenning taxied up to it and throttled back; then he reached out and switched off the engine. The propeller kicked and came to rest, and the silence of the evening closed on us again.

Stenning heaved himself up out of the rear cockpit and jumped down; he was in plus fours and a flying helmet. Joan came climbing down the plane from the front seat.

“Had a good trip?” I asked.

“Thick as far as Salisbury,” said Stenning. He pulled his helmet off and smoothed his hair. “You’ve got it nice down here.”

Joan dropped down on to the ground. She had taken off her helmet, and she shook her shingled hair into some sort of order. “Cheer–oh, Malcolm,” she remarked. “You’re looking very fit.”

“So I am,” I said. “A bat or two still flying round the belfry, perhaps, but nothing to make a song about.” I turned to Sixpence: “Joan, I want you to meet Miss Gordon. She’s staying here with me for a few days.”

Lady Stenning stopped scratching her hair and composed her features into a smile. “Afternoon,” she said. “I hope he’s been remembering his duties as a host. He doesn’t often, I may say.”

Sixpence smiled diffidently, and said: “Good afternoon.”

I turned to Stenning. He was staring at Mollie in perplexity, slowly passing one hand over his disordered hair. “But we’ve met before,” he said. “Of course we have.” He looked inquiringly at her. “Now where the devil was that?”

I asked in some surprise: “Do you two know each other, then?”

“I’m damn sure we do,” said Sir Philip. “We’ve met some place or other.” He smiled at her. “I’m so sorry, but I can’t just pin it down.”

I glanced at Mollie. She caught my eye despairingly, sending an appeal for help. Something was evidently wrong; I didn’t know what, but I did all I could to help her out. “Perhaps you met him at some party,” I remarked. “I’ve often met people like that, and couldn’t think of where we’d met before.”

She forced a smile. “We did meet once before. But I didn’t know you were Sir Philip Stenning, then.”

“Don’t suppose I was,” said Stenning equably. “But where was it that we met?”

There was nothing for it, then. “In the Salford Road Palais de Danse,” said Mollie bravely. “In Manchester—about two years ago. You came in one night with a party, rather late, and booked me for the evening.”

There was a momentary silence after that—the very slightest pause. I moved to her and slipped my arm through hers. “Miss Gordon teaches dancing in the North,” I said easily. “She’s spending her summer holiday down here with me.”

Stenning had recovered by that time. “By God, yes,” he replied. “I remember now. I was with Dick Annesley and Holt. I say, it’s splendid meeting you again down here.”

And Joan said practically: “Now’s the time to get my quick–step right. Philip’s always going on at me because I can’t do enough tricks.” She turned to Mollie: “I’d love it if you’d show me, some time.”

I sent a little message of my thanks to Joan. “Of course, I’d love to, Lady Stenning,” Mollie said. “I know some lovely new ones that Pagani did last season, ever so pretty.”

“That’s a bet,” said Joan. We tinned to pushing the machine towards the barn. Before the opening Stenning folded back the wings; we pushed the Moth in under cover and collected their belongings from the locker. Then we made off towards the house, the girls walking ahead of Stenning and myself.

We went inside and Mollie went upstairs with Joan; Stenning and I turned into the library for a drink. He raised it with a meaning twinkle in his eye. “Luck!” he said. “Boys will be boys.”

I met his glance. “I brought her down from Leeds three days ago,” I said simply. “She’s in this business that you want to know about. Norman had a good go at her yesterday, but he didn’t get much out of her.”

He raised his eyebrows, swallowed down his drink, and set the glass down on the table by his side. “You’ve got to keeping some damn funny company, these days,” he said. “Not but what the girl’s all right. Nice, quiet little bit—or was when I met her. But I’d never have thought to find you with the CID.”

I nodded. “You’re right there. I’ve had my fill of your friend Norman in the last two days.”

I told him that we’d have a talk about it after dinner, and took him up and showed him to his room. Mollie was in her room with Joan; I heard them talking as we passed the door. It seemed that they were getting on all right; I might have known I could rely on Joan. I passed along and saw that Stenning had everything he wanted in his place; then I went to my own room to wash.

I forget what we talked about that night at dinner, but it went all right. The party had settled down, and Mollie was no longer shy of Joan. I sat on with Stenning after dinner in the dining–room, after the ladies had gone through into the south room, and over the port I told him everything I knew about the business.

He was intensely interested. He told me that Norman had been on to him in London to find out what he had heard in Rotterdam; he had had some dealings with Norman previously in his chequered career, and knew Sir David Carter. I found that he had told Norman a great deal more about the episode in Rotterdam than he had mentioned on the yacht. It seemed to hinge about a conversation in a café on the quays, and it went somehow like this:

Stenning had gone to this café for a drink. He was with another man, some engineer or pilot from the aerodrome, and they sat down in the sunshine at a table on the pavement outside. The window of the place was open above their heads and the door was open at their side; in this position they could not be seen from inside the café premises.

They sat there for the most part in silence, not having much to say to each other, sipping their drinks and looking out over the harbour. Inside the room some conversation was in progress about a shipping contract, the majority of which they overheard through door and window. Stenning sat there on the pavement in the sun, listening idly, not taking very much in. In fact, he never really thought of it again until he spoke of carpet sweepers to me that evening on the yacht.

The conversation was in English. One of the talkers was apparently the captain of a vessel, a young man by the voice, educated, and English. The other one was probably a Dutchman or a German, speaking English with a strong accent. Stenning never saw either of the speakers.

The contract was for shipping carpet sweepers and relays—electrical relays, perhaps, but Stenning did not know. Fifteen sweepers and thirty–eight relays were involved; the smallness of these quantities mildly attracted his attention. Delivery was to be made to Berth No. 16A; an advice note had been sent to the Professor. Stenning heard nothing to explain who the Professor was.

That was all he could remember of the conversation, which indeed had hardly attracted his attention at the time. Later on the same afternoon, however, he had occasion to go down to the docks to see to the unloading of an engine in connection with his work. Walking along the quays he recollected berth No. 16A, and had the curiosity to look and see what sort of vessel was involved. He found a small, single–masted sailing vessel of some forty or fifty tons, a sloop or bawley—he would not be certain which. She was an English rig. He only gave her a casual glance, for he was in a hurry. His impression was of a vessel that was little more than a smack; he retained the memory, however, of a cargo hatch. A crabber, or some vessel of that sort.

That was the sum of Stenning’s evidence. It had not provided Norman with a lot to go upon, because Stenning had seen neither of the talkers and was by no means sure that he would be able to identify the boat again. He had only looked down on her, quite casually, from the top of the quay.

Norman had made a search through the police archives at the yard for the Professor, and had found at least fifteen. He said that every gang in his experience possessed some member, generally of a higher standard of intelligence than the others, who was described like that.

I sat on for some time in the dining–room discussing it with Stenning, but we didn’t get much forrader. Finally the clock struck ten, and roused me to the time. It was over an hour since the ladies had gone out and left us talking with the port. I got a little worried then that Sixpence might have fallen down and hurt herself with Joan, and so I rose, and we went through to the south room.

As it turned out, I need not have been alarmed. We found them playing the gramophone and talking about knitted cross–stitch jumpers, or something of that sort, and eating a box of chocolates that Joan must have brought down with her. I could see that they were getting on all right, and I heaved a sigh of relief. I had had visions of finding them silent in opposite comers of the room; one never knows with girls. Or I don’t, anyway.

It was a warm, still, summer night. We walked out on to the terrace in the dusk and stood there looking out over the Range, talking idly about the chance of the weather and the sea in the next few days. Stenning was going west next day in the Irene; I had other plans, myself, and thought of taking Sixpence east.

In the dim light she came to me and said: “Please, Commander Stevenson, I think I’m going up to bed, if you don’t mind. I do feel ever so sleepy.”

“Right–o,” I said; “I’m going soon myself.” I paused. “I thought if it’s a fine day tomorrow we’d have an early breakfast and take Runagate.”

She looked up at me, puzzled. “Please—I didn’t understand.”

I smiled. “It’s the name of my yacht,” I said. “Runagate. I thought we might go sailing all day if it’s fine. Would you like that?”

She beamed at me. “It would be ever so lovely to do that. I’ve only been in a sailing boat once, and it was quite rough, and ever such fun.” She paused reminiscently. “The gentleman that took me, he was sick.”

Stenning laughed. “Red hot!” he said.

She laughed with him. “He was cross—what with being with me, and the others laughing at him….” Her voice drifted away to silence in the dusk; a veil dropped upon the story of that pleasure party. “Goodnight,” she said, and moved quietly away into the house.

I turned to Stenning and Joan. “We’d better get off early.” I said, thinking of the tides. “Breakfast at eight—not later, or we’ll find ourselves sweating out over the flood.”

“I thought of that,” said Stenning. “We’ll sail together.” I took a turn or two with them upon the terrace before going up. At the corner of the house, in Mollie’s room, I saw the light come on and shine out in the night. I saw her shadow move and pass upon the curtains of the room. I knew that Joan was watching, too; I stirred and glanced at her, and our eyes met.

“Malcolm,” said Joan, “who is she?” Her curiosity, I suppose was irresistible. “I mean,” she said, “it’s so unlike you to have anyone.”

I eyed her grimly. I knew I had to face this questioning, this prying into my affairs. “She’s just a girl that I picked up in Leeds and brought down here,” I said defensively. “I gave her ten pounds to come.”

Joan laughed softly. “You are a funny old stick,” she said, quite quietly. “You needn’t think you’re going to kid me she’s that sort of girl, or you’re that sort of man.” She paused. “As a matter of fact, she told me all about her work, and how you came to meet. But then there was a lot more that I didn’t quite get the hang of; I don’t know that she really understood it all herself. All about her brother, and a fire in a motor–lorry, and the police, and staying on to have a holiday with you.”

She stopped, and there was a little silence on the terrace; Stenning had walked a little way away. “Well,” I said, “she seems to have told you all there is to tell. I haven’t anything to add to it.”

She stood and eyed me for a moment. And then, quite unexpectedly, she said: “I think you must have been rather a dear.”

I stood by the parapet looking out over the harbour mouth; the moon was coming up in a calm night, and there were wreaths of fog or mist down by the sea. “Stenning will tell you all I know,” I said at last. “I got involved in this when I was drunk, and played a dirty trick on her. And then I didn’t like it when I’d done it. That was all.”

I didn’t feel inclined to tell her any more, and she didn’t worry me to do so. So we took a turn or two upon the terrace, till Stenning said: “I vote we go to bed.”

“We’d better have a whisky first,” I said. Joan said goodnight to us, and moved towards the house. I went with her to the window; on the threshold of the room she turned to me, and said:

“You’re very lucky, Malcolm. I think she’s simply sweet.” Then she was gone before I could reply, before I could ask her to explain herself.

I went with Stenning to the model room, and we had our whisky there. He wanted the Irene got up on the slip as soon as he came back; he said she wanted caulking at the stem post. She didn’t, as it happened; what she wanted was new stuffing at the stern tube gland. I fixed up this with him, and then we too went up to bed.

I was up early the next day, but Sixpence was before us. I heard her go downstairs as I was shaving, and saw her in the garden with the Rogers’ dog. It was a misty sort of morning with blue sky above; not a breath of wind. I knew what that would mean for the day’s sailing—getting up sails that flapped about and didn’t draw, and trundling along under power most of the day. Still, it should be calm enough, and it seemed to me that there might be a little wind from the east to bring us home in the late afternoon.

I found her in the garden when I got down, and walked with her for a little time among the rose beds on the dewy paving. Then we went back into the house; Stenning was there in sea clothes, dirty flannel trousers and a fisherman’s jersey. Then Joan came down in much the same sort of getup. I saw Sixpence looking at them furtively, and smiled. “You’re not dirty enough for this game,” I said.

“I didn’t know,” she murmured. “I thought you always did yachting in white clothes.”

“Not this sort,” said Stenning. “That’s only when you don’t know how to sail a boat and have to have a crew.” I think that was unjust, but Stenning hates a crew. So do I for that matter; paid hands are nothing but a nuisance on a boat.

She said again: “I didn’t know. I thought yachts always had a crew, like on the pictures.”

Joan laughed, and helped herself to sausages. “They don’t do any washing up upon the pictures,” she observed. “Or perhaps that’s what the crew’s for. My experience is that a woman’s place upon a yacht is at the tub.”

We finished breakfast and collected all their gear together with a hamper of our own containing lunch, packed everything into the Bentley, and set off for the yard. Down by the harbour everything was wreathed in mist, thin, with a visibility of half a mile or so. I knew that this would clear off as the day went on; we often have it that way in the summer time.

At the yard we separated. Joan and Stenning started to unload their stuff into their dinghy, and I went into my office for a few minutes to go through the post. There wasn’t very much to do; I came out presently and saw them pulling out to the Irene. My pram was at the steps; I took Sixpence down and put her in the stern sheets with the hamper, took the sculls, and set out towards Runagate in the next berth.

Sixpence sat trailing her fingers idly in the water as we went. “It’s lovely here,” she said, quite quietly. The mist curled round the hills in slow, thin wreaths; the day was very still. I glanced over my shoulder. “That’s the vessel,” I remarked to her. “The white cutter.”

I brought the dinghy alongside, stood up, and held her off from the topsides. “Hop on board,” I said; she slipped nimbly from the little pram on to the deck and stooped to take the hamper that I handed up to her. I let the dinghy drop astern, and followed her on deck. “What do you think of her?” I asked.

She stood there for a moment very still upon the deck before replying, looking round about. “It’s all so … clean,” she said at last. She looked along the sweet sheer to the bows. “It’s beautiful,” she said. “The way that she goes up like that in front.”

I stared at her in surprise; she had picked on one of the outstanding features of the vessel. “You’ve never seen a boat like this before?” I asked. “Nor been to sea?”

She shook her head. “Only in the speedboats at Bridlington, and that time we went sailing that I told you about.”

I pursued the point of curiosity. “How did you know that it was right for her to be like that? That sheer up to the bows?”

She stared at me in perplexity. “The sea wouldn’t come over so much, would it?”

I stood and looked at her. “You must have had to do with ships to know that much,” I said. “Think, now.”

She shook her head. “Only my grandpa. He used to work in some place where ships were built, in Scotland. But he died when I was small.”

I nodded slowly, and we went below. She followed me, wondering, as I showed her through the ship. The forecastle, she thought, was terribly small to do the cooking in. She fell in love with the saloon, with the satinwood panels, with the little racks and cupboards, with the recording aneroid in springs. She didn’t quite know what to say about the sleeping cabin, with the engine casing down between the bunks.

She turned to me at last: “It would be fun to really live upon a boat like this—for weeks, like.”

I smiled. “You’d like it?” I inquired. “It’s very rough sometimes, you know.”

She nodded. “Fancy sleeping in these little beds….”

I took her up on deck again, and we began preparing to cast off. She was intelligent and quick about the deck; I was continually reminded that she was a dancer as she moved nimbly on the cluttered, narrow deck. Together we got the dinghy alongside, shackled the burton to her bows, and shifted her on board. It was simple getting under way in that dead calm; as soon as the engine was running smoothly beneath our feet I went forward and cast off the mooring chain. The buoy and light line followed with a splash, and we drifted slowly clear.

Stenning cast off almost simultaneously with us. I put the clutch in and the vessel forged ahead in the thin mist, with Stenning following in our wake. He hailed us presently and I slowed down for him to come up on us a bit; he ranged Irene alongside, a ship’s length away as we went down the river.

“Malcolm,” said Joan, “got any salt to spare? We’ve only got a little in this pot, and I’m putting on a stew.”

I turned to Mollie. “Come and take her for a minute while I go below,” I said. She came and took the little wheel, protesting that she didn’t know about it; in the Irene Joan and Stenning stood and watched us, grinning. I stood with her for a minute showing her how it went, then handed it to her. “Now, keep her bowsprit on that point of land.” She took it all in, grimly serious. “Give us a decent berth,” I said to Stenning, and went down below to look for salt.

There was silence up on deck, so far as there is ever silence in a vessel under way. Once, as I rummaged in the cupboards, I heard Stenning say quietly: “Other way; put it the other way. That’s right, now steady her at that.” In the stern the motor chugged on easily; at the bows I heard the tinkling ripple from the cutwater. I made a little paper screw of salt for them and took it up on deck; we were cruising steadily beside Irene and heading directly for the point. “Let her come up a little now,” I said. “About a hand’s span from the point.” The vessel swung and steadied on her course.

“Like that?” asked Mollie.

I nodded. “That’ll do.”

The water of the harbour mouth was glassy calm, boiling a little here and there with eddies from the tide. Stenning ranged his vessel alongside and Joan reached out and took the salt from me, than they sheered off again. Mollie made as if to give the helm to me.

“Keep it a bit,” I said; “you’re doing fine.” I glanced ahead. “Keep on as she is; you don’t want to go too near the point.” I got out of the cockpit and went forward on the deck, and began trimming her for sea.

We passed the Battery and motored out into the Range. At sea the mist was still hanging about in wreaths, the visibility perhaps a mile. I finished my jobs forward and came aft again, and went down into the saloon to fetch a cushion for Sixpence at the wheel.

She beamed at me: “I do think this is lovely.”

I nodded: “A good game.”

In the Range we parted company with the Irene; Stenning was going on down west to Salcombe and the Yealm. At the Mewstone I put her round and headed up along the coast for Berry Head. It was still thick. I put her on a compass course and taught Sixpence to read the card; she was still steering the vessel, keen and engrossed. And then I rested for a little in the cockpit, leaning on the hatch and staring out ahead. I would never have believed that any girl would pick it up so soon. It was in her blood, of course; that shipwright grandfather of hers was probably the last of a long line of merchant seamen. Seafaring is hereditary, I think; I find it so with my own shipwrights in the yard.

The mist grew thinner as we drew near Berry Head; it wreathed apart to show the great, familiar bluff and I felt a faint puff of air upon my cheek. We drew abreast the Head and I put her on another compass course; the wind was steadying down into the east, a light air to the heated land. I went forward and broke out the jib; it flapped and drew lazily in the sun. I gave her the balloon foresail as well, and went back aft; I stopped the motor and we went slipping slowly on under headsails alone. I was in no mood to hurry that day.

“It’s lovely, going on like this without the motor,” Mollie said. “Quiet, like.”

For an hour we drifted on like that, enshrouded in the mist, basking in the sun upon the hot teak of the cockpit and the hatch. Once a Brixham vessel loomed up through the haze and crossed our bows, a great tanned ketch moving slowly under full sail, majestic and imposing on the water’s face. On our beam the land showed faintly, Paignton way; occasionally we heard faint sounds of motor horns and barking dogs. For anyone who prided himself on seamanship it was a shocking way to drift across the bay, under headsails only on a day like that. Still, it was pleasant in the sun.

Then Sixpence roused me. “Oh,” she said, “what’s that?” And pointed dead ahead.

The sun and the light wind were banishing the mist. In front of us the confines of the bay were visible, the flat land rising up into tall cliffs at the north end. There were hills there, and a wonderful town upon the hills that followed the slopes down to the tideway; a magic town, built of white harbour walls and gleaming palaces beside the sea. All this was still half shrouded in the mist; in the bright sun it was all shot with colours, gold and blue.

Like a flight of rose leaves, fluttering in a mist
Of opal, and ruby, and pearl, and amethyst….

“Oh,” she said again, and turned to me, entranced. “What place is that?”

I glanced ahead, and turned to knock my pipe out on the rail. “That?” I said. “Oh, that’s Torquay.”

I heard her breathe: “Torquay … ” and fell to filling up my pipe again. And so we stood like that for a little time until she took her eyes from it, and came to me, and said:

“You’re ever so good to me, Commander Stevenson. I don’t know what to say….”

I muttered: “That’s all right.” And then quite quickly, before I knew what she was going to do, she reached right up and kissed me on the cheek.

I put an arm round her, the hand that hadn’t got my pipe and pouch in it, and held her for a minute there upon tiptoe; then I let her down again upon her feet. “That was very nice,” I said, and grinned at her. I stood there holding her like that with one arm round her shoulders while I pointed out to her the harbour and the pier; I’m not so sure that she was paying much attention. And presently I left her and went forward to uncast the stoppers on the anchor and its chain, and she went back to con the vessel in. And so that moment passed.

I dropped anchor in four fathoms about two cables from the westward harbour pier; it was about half tide. Sixpence came forward from the idle wheel and watched me veer the chain; then for a quarter of an hour we leaned on the main–boom and watched the crowds upon the shore through field–glasses. Then we went below to change for her bathe; first on deck, I got the dinghy alongside to make it easy for her to get out.

She came on deck at last in her green bathing dress; on the harbour wall I saw the telescopes come up at us. We dived in together; she turned and swam to the bows and hung on to the bob stay and the chain, laughing at me, then to the dinghy and so out on deck. I went in again alone; Sixpence was for the sun and the warm woodwork of the deck.

“I do think Lady Stenning’s awfully nice,” she said as we sat there.

I blew a cloud of smoke. “That’s what I told you, but you wouldn’t have it.”

She wrinkled up her brows. “I know. But she didn’t seem like a Lady, not to talk to.”

“Well,” I said, “she wasn’t one last year.”

She pondered over this for a bit. “She was ever so nice to me,” she said at last.

Presently we went down to the saloon and dressed. Rogers had put us up a sort of picnic lunch: a dressed crab and Chablis, and some sweet or other. We took it up and ate it in the cockpit in the sun. I had put on the Primus and we had a cup of coffee after it and sat there smoking for a time, lazily studying the shore and town.

Then we went on shore. I sculled the dinghy in through the entrance to the harbour and in among the yachts moored there in rows; Tern IV was there, and Coral, I remember. We went on and left the dinghy in the inner harbour; up the steps to the quay, and there we were before the shops.

We wandered round that town all afternoon. Sixpence had reached the Mecca of her dreams, the Torquay that had meant so much to her throughout her life, and she was missing none of it. We went from the harbour to the pier and then into the gardens where the band was playing; we looked at the sunshine register and saw the veritable Station Road itself. Then we went back and found the Palais and had a look at the outside of that, and then we had to locate Bay View Hotel, where a friend of hers had spent a holiday one summer with a gentleman, and had a lovely time. And then we went to look at shops.

And then that damnable affair cropped up again. It was in the main street that it happened; I wish to God we’d gone back to the boat. We’d got about half way along a line of shops, with Sixpence studying entranced a great variety of articles from furniture to shoes, when we came to a window that displayed a considerable amount of ladies’ underwear. I stood there while she glued her nose against the pane, hoping that nobody I knew would pass that way. And suddenly she plucked my arm.

“Oh, look,” she said. “That’s where Edna works.”

She pointed to a ladies’ dummy elegantly attired in nothing but a corset, and inadequate at that. “Slimline corsetry,” she said. “That’s where she works. I wonder if she made that one?”

I didn’t understand. “Who’s Edna?” I inquired.

She turned to me. “Didn’t I tell you about her in the Leeds Palais? She’s Billy’s girl.” She paused. “Only she doesn’t seem to care about him, not like he does her.”

There seemed to be a sort of silence then; in the busy street the traffic moved about us, but before the window we were very still. This was the first that I had heard of this young woman, but I knew just what it meant. If anyone could tell where Billy was, it would be this girl Edna in her corset factory.

I think she saw that it was something serious. “I hadn’t heard of her,” I said at last. “Where is it that she works?”

She said: “It’s Hammersmith. But I did tell you, back in the police station that day. I asked if Billy’d gone to Hammersmith.”

She had, and I had shut her up, and then I had forgotten it. By some chance it had not come out in Norman’s questioning that this girl might know where he was; this was the first that we had heard of her.

“Do you think she’d know where Billy is?” I asked.

Something of the hard and anxious look that she had had in the dance hall came back to her as she looked up at me. A shadow had come to dull the brightness of our day—God knows, it isn’t often that one gets a day like that. It might have happened at some other time.

“I think she would,” she said.

We turned and went back to the dinghy at the harbour steps.

Chapter 13

We were dead tired when the anchor dropped. Stenning came stumbling aft down from the bows, walking like a drunken man and muttering about a riding light. I clambered stiffly from the wheelhouse and looked round; in the Cattewater it seemed immensely calm and quiet, and the ship was still. Fleming came up and sat upon his engine hatch, and for a few minutes we stood there together, watching the lights from the town reflected on the rippled, oily sea. We had been out for little more than twenty hours, but we were very, very tired. It was the seasickness that did it, I suppose—that and the short, uneasy motion of the tug, that gave no rest.

At last I stirred. “Got to go on shore,” I muttered. I turned to Stenning: “See if you can get Mount Batten or the Citadel with that signal lamp, and ask them to send a boat, or have one sent. Say that it’s urgent. I’m going aft to turn those policemen out.”

I went down to the cuddy. They were sprawling on the bench seats, fast asleep; I stood there swaying in the fœtid, reeking air, fumbling to light the lamp that hangs upon the bulkhead. They must have had a rotten time of it. Most of the time they had been battened down below; I had not felt that I could trust them upon deck in the conditions we had had, and it had been impossible to keep the cuddy open in that sea. They lay on the benches sleeping, exhausted and ill. I bent over the sergeant and shook him into wakefulness.

“Wake your man and come on deck,” I said. “We’re anchored in the Cattewater—at Plymouth. It’s about one o’clock, or getting on that way. We’re going ashore in a few minutes now.”

I went on deck again, glad to get out of the place, and found Stenning busy at the signal lamp. He had got a reply from the Mount Batten seaplane station, and he was talking to them in quick flashes of Morse code. At last he stood up and turned to me:

“I think they’re sending out a launch.”

We stood and waited in the cold, dark night, interminably. From the shore we heard the whistling of trains and the long clank of shunting in the goods yard. The police came up and joined us by the engine–room, walking unsteadily upon the deck. At last we heard the motor of the launch; it came alongside with a sergeant in charge, and we persuaded it to take us to the Citadel.

It was striking one o’clock when we got on shore. The policemen led the way, and Stenning and I followed in their wake, down the long, empty streets towards the police station.

They knew about us there, but they had heard nothing of the wreck out at the Shackles. Nobody had seen that vessel go on shore. “They went on the Shackles in trying to get away from us,” I said. The police confirmed what I said, and that tale went, and has done till this day.

They got through on the telephone to Dartmouth and I spoke a little to Norman at the police station there. I told him briefly my version of what had occurred; that we had been sticking to their heels and waiting till some vessel came to help, and that in trying to shake off our pursuit they had gone ashore. I said that we had done everything that could be done, which was as true as made no matter. And then I said that I was coming back to Dartmouth as soon as I could get a car.

I asked how Mollie and Fedden were getting on. He said: “Both going on quite all right, I believe. To tell the truth, I’ve not had time to bother about them for the last few hours. That was at about six o’clock when I heard last. Fedden was the one they were concerned about—the shock, you know. The girl was getting on quite well.”

I told him that I was going to try and get a car, and rang off. There was some business then with the police; the whole coast had to be patrolled for bodies or other evidence that might be washed ashore for fifteen miles each side of the Dodman, and it was evidently necessary that the watchers should be out by dawn. That took a bit of arranging, and it was nearly three o’clock when Stenning and I and the two policemen bundled sleepily into the car that was to drive us home.

That run seemed interminable. I do it in forty minutes in the Bentley; in that car it took an hour and a half. It was cold, too. By the time we crawled up the last hill to my house it was full dawn; Stenning and I got out on the gravel in front of my house and stared at each other in the clear, fresh morning light. It was about thirty hours since we had left the house.

“Bath,” said Stenning sourly. “God, you want a shave.”

We went into the house and he went on upstairs. I paused for a minute, and sat down to the telephone. I rang up the nursing home—the same that I had visited from time to time. The matron answered me.

“Commander Stevenson this end,” I said. “I rang up to inquire how Colonel Fedden and Miss Gordon were getting on. I’ve just got back.”

She said: “Oh, Colonel Fedden’s through the worst of it. We were a little worried this afternoon; the shock, you know. He’s not a young man, is he? And it does tell, for all that he keeps himself so fit. But I think that’s all over. He’s having a lovely sleep now. I really don’t think you need worry about him at all, Commander.”

“That’s fine,” I said. “What about Miss Gordon?”

There was a momentary pause, and then she said: “Oh, well, I think she’s going on as well as could be expected, you know.” She repeated: “Oh, yes, as well as could be expected. Of course, you can’t expect her to be quite the same as Colonel Fedden, can you?”

I said: “Do you mean she’s ill?”

“Oh no. Just a little temperature, you know; nothing to worry about. She’s rather restless—” She broke off. “Oh, there is Dr Dixon, just coming out of her room now. Would you like to have a word with him?”

I said: “I should.”

Dixon came to the telephone. He asked where I was speaking from, and then:

“I think you’d better come down here,” he said. “Yes; I rather want to see you. Yes; it’s about the girl. I think it might be a good thing to have another opinion—things move so quickly in these cases, you know. Anyway, we’ll have a talk about it when you come down.”

I nodded slowly. “I’ll be with you in ten minutes,” I replied, and rang him off.

The sun was just rising as I went through to the stable yard; it came up behind a bank of watery clouds; the gale was dying with the dawn. I opened the stable gates and got the Bentley out, and ran down to the nursing home. I found Dixon in the surgery, and he got up to meet me as I came in.

I went straight to the point. “This girl,” I said. “I take it that you mean there’s something wrong.”

He met my eyes. “I hope not,” he replied. “The position is this. She was all right till nine o’clock last night. Then the temperature began, and the pulse went up in sympathy—you understand.”

I nodded. “What’s the temperature now?”

“A hundred and three point five.”

“And the pulse?”

“About a hundred and forty.”

I said: “And what is it you think she’s got?”

He hesitated. “Provisionally, I am treating for septicæmia. That is—what I should be apprehensive of.”

There was a little silence in the room. “Is there anything else that it could be?” I asked.

He said something a little diffidently about coincidences: I gathered that he was thinking of measles or something of that sort. Frankly, he did not think that that was very probable. And then he said that if it was septicæmia he would prefer to have some help. “Things change, you know—the treatments,” he said, a little apologetically. “It’s some time since I had a case like this. Now, Holderness over at Plymouth, I know he had three at least last year—he was dining with me the other night. I think it might be as well to have him over.”

I nodded. “By all means. Get on to him at once.”

He went out of the room to get the matron to put through the call for him, and when he came back I asked him: “Who’s the authority on this time at the present time?”

He glanced at me. “You mean in this part of the world?”

“In England. Harley Street.”

He considered for a moment, and absently turned a pile of periodicals upon his desk. “I don’t think Harley Street,” he said at last. “I think you’d have to go to Liverpool, perhaps. Sir Donald McKenzie—he’s the chap that writes so much about it, and he certainly has done wonderful work on it up there.”

I nodded. “We’d better get him down,” I said. “At once.” I paused. “Get a call through to him, and tell him to fly down if he can. If not, to telegraph what time he can reach Exeter—I’ll have the car to meet him there.” I turned and stared him grimly in the eyes. “You understand? He’s to drop everything, and come at once. He is to start within an hour from now.”

“Well, of course,” said Dixon, “if you do that you’ll get the very best advice obtainable.” He hesitated for a moment. “And, of course, you’ll have to pay for it.”

I asked: “How much?”

Dixon hesitated. “I really couldn’t say. It is conceivable that if I ask him to drop everything as you suggest and fly down here, he might charge as much as two hundred guineas. I should not say it would be more.”

I nodded slowly, and the room seemed to nod with me: I steadied myself by the table, for I was very tired. “Offer five hundred on the telephone,” I said wearily. “Get him to come at any price he wants.”

I sat down on a chair; Dixon stood eyeing me. And then he said: “I’m very sorry, Stevenson. You can depend upon us to do everything that can be done, regardless of expense.”

I raised my heavy head. “You can have carte blanche up to ten thousand pounds,” I said. “I’ll give you that in writing, if you like. And after that as much more as you want.”

He left me then to telephone, and I sat on there in the surgery for what seemed many hours, until he came again. “McKenzie arrives at Exeter at 2.15,” he said. “That is the best that I could do. And Holderness is on his way here now.”

I got on to my feet. “Good man,” I said. And then I said, a little timidly: “Do you think I could look in and see her for a bit? Or wouldn’t that be wise?”

“I think it would be excellent,” he said. “She was asking for you all day yesterday. But you don’t want to go in there like that.”

“Like what?” I asked stupidly.

He laughed and swung a mirrored door till I could see myself. I was still in sea clothes, serge trousers and blue jersey, and an oilskin over all. I had a growth of stubble straggling across my face, and the features that looked back at me were lined and worn. Dixon laughed. “Get along back and have a bath and shave, and come down when you’ve had some breakfast,” he said. “I’ll expect you here at about eight o’clock.”

Stenning had gone to bed, and was asleep when I got back. I left him there and went and had a bath, and shaved, and dressed carefully and neatly that disastrous day. When I had finished, I looked in the glass. Everything was neat and orderly except my face, which was all grey, the face of an old man. I went downstairs to my ruined dining–room and poured a whisky from the decanter which was still upon the table, and with that inside me I felt more myself.

Rogers brought me breakfast in the library, but I didn’t fancy it. By eight o’clock I was down at the nursing home, and waiting in the surgery till Dixon came.

I heard him coming down the passage from her room, talking incisively to the matron, and I saw his face before he knew that I was there. He brightened when he saw me. “That’s better,” he remarked. He said that Holderness had been there and had seen the girl, and had gone away to have some breakfast. I gathered that he had not been of much help, and that the thing would have to run its course without much check, pending the arrival of the specialist.

“She’s been asking after you again,” said Dixon. “I think it might be a good thing if you went and sat with her a bit.” He hesitated. “You’ll realise, of course, that she has a high temperature,” he said. “You won’t excite her—she must be kept quite quiet. You may find her wandering a little, too. Still, I think perhaps it might be a good thing if you went and sat there for a bit.”

In the pale room the blinds were still half drawn; a nurse was moving quietly about at the far end. She greeted me with a smile and moved a chair for me beside the bed, and I sat down to throw my weight into the fight. “Don’t worry if she doesn’t know you just at first,” the nurse said quietly behind me. “She will later. She’s been asking for you all the time.”

I sat and stared at Mollie in the bed, flushed and uncomfortable, and most unlike the girl that I had known. I tried to think of something I could say to her as she lay turning restlessly, and staring through the place where I was sitting by her side. And finding nothing I could say, I took one of her hands in mine and sat there stroking it, and listening to the words that dropped from time to time from the hot lips.

And sitting there, I drifted back into another world. The odd phrases and the half sentences were all about her former life, the life that she had lived up in the north. Once came a stanza of a vaudeville song that I remembered seeing early in the war, and there was much about the stage, about soubrettes and leads. There was something of dancing, and of boys. All this came out in little bits and snatches between long, silent intervals of restlessness. Once the nurse came up and looked at her most critically, and felt the pulse. And then she turned to me and said: “She’s ever so much quieter since you came.” And that amazed me.

And presently, when I had been there for perhaps an hour, she suddenly lay quiet and stared at me with dull eyes, but awake. And then she said, quite quietly:

“Is that the Commander?”

“That’s right,” I said, “I’ve come to sit with you for a bit.” And I stroked the hand that I was holding.

She said: “It’s ever so nice of you to come.” And then in explanation she added: “I’ve been such a long way.”

“I know,” I said. “But now you’re home again.”

They turned me out soon after that, telling her that I should come back presently, and I was left to pace the surgery downstairs. Stenning turned up and I told him briefly what was on; he was as powerless as I had been to help. All he could do was to take the burden of negotiations with the police from me, and he left me to go down to Norman to discuss what else had to be done.

I went out at once into the town. At the entrance to the nursing home a young man stopped me, and informed me, a little hesitantly, that he represented the Morning Herald. I told him that I owned thirty per cent of the shares in that publication, that he’d be sacked before the week was out, and he could burn in hell for all I cared. That settled him, but there were others that I could not sack so easily. One took a photograph of me as I went back into the home.

I did not see her again before lunch. Dixon came down and said that I had done a bit of good, and that she was quieter than she had been all the night. I had sent Adams with the car to Exeter to meet McKenzie, and I walked up to my house and snatched a little food, and walked down to the nursing home again, blasting and cursing the reporters who accosted me as I was walking down the street. The town seemed full of them that day, and I walked through them, cursing as I went.

McKenzie proved to be a little sandy–haired man with pince–nez, by no means the great figure I had pictured him. Dixon and Holderness were pleased with him, however, and they took him into consultation in the surgery, and I left with a dozen old copies of the Tatler and Punch that somebody had given me to read. I heard them leave the surgery and go along the passage to her room, and then there was a good deal of movement of the nurses in the home, and passing in and out. And presently, at rather after four o’clock, I heard them coming down the passage. I heard Dixon say: “You might have a word with him now, perhaps. He’s in the other room.” I got up on my feet as they came in to me.

McKenzie started to tell me how ably his colleague, Dr Dixon, had been managing the case, as he was bound to do in etiquette. I cut him short when he was half–way through his piece. “You found a sick girl, I’m afraid,” I said.

The little man shot a quick glance at me. “I’ll not deny it. I’ll not deny it at all, I found a very sick girl. Not that she won’t pull through, mind you. Don’t think it, but she’ll want watching tonight, the while she’s in the worst of it, and she’ll do fine. I was just tellin’ the doctor here, I’ll bide with you tonight.”

I cleared my throat. “That would be very kind of you. I was hoping that perhaps you’d stay the night.”

He went into the details of the treatment in his dry Scots way—something to do with scarlet fever anti–toxin, which I have forgotten now. We stood there talking for a quarter of an hour, until he said:

“Well, now. Ye’ll go and sit with her a bit?” He changed to a command. “Ye’ll go away and have a bit of tea, and ye’ll come back at five o’clock and sit with her a while. She likes to have you there, the doctor was telling me. And, man, it’s what she wants she’s got to have this night.”

He eyed me narrowly, this little sandy man. “The doctor was telling me she thinks the world and all of you. Don’t think because I’ve come from Liverpool that I’m the one that’s going to get her through the night. It’s you. Now, are you up to it?” He shot the question at me as a challenge, peering at me through his pince–nez.

I met his eyes. “Three nights ago I asked her if she would become my wife,” I said. “I’ll do all I can.”

He turned away. “Weel, ye can’t do more than that.” He turned again. “Just stamina, that’s a’ she wants. Ye can’t build up physique by dancing underground all afternoon and half the night, and lying abed all morn. And ye canna pump it in with an hypodermic squirt. Good food and exercise, and plenty sleep. That’s all she’s wanting. Ye’d better give it her when this thing’s over.”

“Just stamina,” he said. “Losh, if you pump that into her I’ll throw me anti–toxins down the sink!” And laughed at his own joke.

I made arrangements on the telephone for a room for him at my house, but it was evident he didn’t contemplate much sleep that night. And then, obediently, I went and had my tea, and at five o’clock I went into her room to battle for her life.

She was awake and smiled to see me come, and I bent down and kissed her on the lips, regardless of the nurse. It seemed to me that she was less restless than she had been before, but every bit as hot; she was noticeably weaker than she had been in the morning. I sat down beside her bed and took her hand in mine, and I began to talk to her about the first things that came into my head.

If I were to try and put down all I said to her that night I should fill many volumes of this ledger, for I talked for hours. She said very little in reply; I sat there stroking her hand and arm, and every now and then she squeezed my hand a little, and smiled up at me. I started off with what we’d do as soon as she was fit to leave the nursing home. I told her that I’d get her moved back into her own room and bathroom in my house as soon as possible, and for that she smiled, and murmured: “I’d love to be there.” And I told her how she could sit out in the sun in the garden all day till her shoulder healed, and read magazines and look out over the flowers at the harbour and the sea. And I told her that I’d get her a kitten to keep her company while I was away at the office in the mornings.

And then, without heeding that the nurse was there, I told her again that I loved her, and she lay there smiling at me with her eyes. I told her that I wanted her to marry me as soon as she felt she could, and if she felt she couldn’t just at first we’d go away together as she wanted, and we’d get married when she liked. I told her that we’d go away and have a real holiday together, a holiday that would go on for as long as we wanted to. And that would be the first real holiday that I had taken since the war.

I told her that we’d start off at Torquay, and she smiled up at me, and whispered: “Lovely.” I said I’d have the Runagate round there, and we’d live in a fine hotel just up above the harbour, in a double room, and we’d spend every day sailing and bathing together, and motoring upon the moors. And she could teach me to dance really properly at night, so that she could dance with me with pleasure all our lives. She said: “You’ll learn ever so quick.”

I told her that we’d stay there for as long as ever she liked, but that once or twice we’d just run up to town to buy her clothes. And I told her that she could have her frocks designed for her, but that I wanted one that would be like the silver and blue one she had worn in the evenings at my house; she must have one like that. And I said that Joan would help her and show her where to buy the things, and where to go for everything she wanted. And then we’d come back to Torquay and she could learn to drive a car, and I’d get her a little light saloon that she could drive herself.

And then I told her, as the autumn came, we’d slip across to the New World. Because once, so many years ago, I met an old merchant skipper—not one of my men—who told me that of all the places that he had seen all through the world there was one that was so supremely beautiful that it stood out like a mountain over all the lovely sights that he had ever seen.

That was the harbour at Halifax in the fall of the year. He pictured it to me as a wide inlet between wooded hills, and full of wooded islands on the water’s face. And all these woods were maple woods, so that in the autumn they turned bright scarlet. With the calm water, the red woods, and the long, cloudless, pale blue autumn days it made a picture that that old man had carried with him all his life; he had longed to return to it again before he died. And it had bitten deep into me, too, so that I told her we would go and see it as the autumn drew on.

And then we’d go on to New York and see the greatest city of the century, so great that the foreigner is faintly homesick when he leaves. I told her that we’d stay there, possibly, till Christmas time, learning about America, and seeing how they lived. I told her, if she liked, we’d go across to Hollywood and see how films were made.

And then I told her that we’d come back home and go to Switzerland. Because by that time her arm would be quite strong again and she could learn to ski, and I told her about the snow and ski–ing and the skating, and the sitting in the blazing sun to eat your lunch on the veranda of the hotel above the snow. I told her about the joy of running on good snow in the sunshine, sweeping in stemming christies down the slopes to the inevitable drink of ice–cold milk in the châlet at the bottom. I told her about the hotels and the snow mountains, rose coloured in the sunset, and I told her about the people that she’d meet, and the dancing in the evenings, where nobody would be so good as her.

They came in then to do something to her, Dixon and McKenzie, and they sent me from the bed. After a quarter of an hour they went away, and I came back to her and took up my tale again where I had left it off. And I told her that in the spring we’d come back home and live at Dartmouth, with the sea and with my ships all summer, because that is home, and one cannot be travelling all the year through. And I told her that I’d teach her how to sail, and that I’d get a little sailing dinghy rigged for her so that she could take her friends out up the river bathing, because it’s warmer up there. And all her friends would come and stay with us from time to time, girls on their one week’s holiday from the grey cities of the north. And she whispered: “I’d have Edna first, if I may.”

And then I told her that we would stay at home for all the summer months, close to the sea, and I would show her the fun of cruising in the English Channel and the West of Ireland. And perhaps, if she wanted to, we’d have one month of that away, and take the car to France, and run down to the south through Chartres and Arles and Avignon, until we reached the sea, to live the Lido life a little at some bathing place. And then back home again, to stay a week in Paris at a quiet place I know that overlooks the Bois, and she could get some shopping done. Then we’d go home, and be at home for August when her friends had holidays.

And in September we might go to Scotland for a little shooting, with some friends of mine.

Evening drew on, and she lay smiling at me there, seeming to drift into a doze, and then rousing again to squeeze my hand. McKenzie came in from time to time to see how she was getting on; the temperature showed no sign of going down. “Ye’ll keep her interest,” he ordered once in a soft tone. “Just keep her interest, and give me drugs a chance….”

I went on talking to her, and I told her that we’d finish up our two–year honeymoon by going round the world. Because I never had seen India, and very little of the East at all, and I was longing to go there with her. I told her that we’d go there with no very settled plan, but that I wanted to go up into Kashmir to see a man who was at school with me, and that I wanted to work down into Ceylon to see the pilgrimage to Adams Peak among the flowers. And then, I said, we’d go on over to Malay and on from Singapore to the South Seas. And there we’d charter a schooner to get off the beaten track, and we’d go cruising through the islands towards Honolulu at the end. Then we would cross to San Francisco and up into Canadian summer in the Rockies, two years hence, and so to Montreal, where I have many friends. And so we’d come back home, after our honeymoon, to settle down to work again, to stay till we were tired and longed to see the world again beyond the sea.

* * * * *

She lay there quiet, in a sort of dream. And about nine o’clock I bent towards her lips, and I heard her say: “I wish the others could have seen us, dear, just once. None of them ever had a gentleman friend like I’ve had.”

I sat with her till far into the night. Then they made me come away, and Dixon took me home.

Chapter 14

I do not think I need put down the events of the succeeding week in any detail. A reliable account of the two inquests came out in The Times, and is available if I should want to look it up—a most improbable contingency. The other newspapers were only fit to burn.

They held the first at Dartmouth upon the two Gordons and the Superintendent. Norman gave evidence in a restricted sort of way. I think that he had had a conversation with the coroner before the case came on, for nothing came out that was of any consequence. They called me next and I swore by Almighty God that the evidence which I should give to that inquest should be the truth, the whole truth, and nothing but the truth; an oath which I took with every intention of committing perjury. But all the evidence they wanted from me was quite formal; I told them something of Mollie and her brother, and their lives. Only one question I remember clearly, when the coroner said delicately: “Are we to understand that these two were related to you in any way, Commander Stevenson?”

I raised my heavy head. “I had asked Miss Gordon if she would do me the honour to become my wife,” I said. “I don’t know if you call that a relationship or not.”

That passed with a little buzz of interest in the court, and next morning I saw a placard close outside my own lodge gates:

Q–BOAT CAPTAIN’S TRAGIC LOVE FOR
MYSTERY DANCING GIRL

Stenning and Joan had wanted to come and stay with me to see it through, but I had told them, brutally perhaps, that I would rather be alone. And so they stayed down in the town, and I went back to build up my old life, working upon the drawings of the little cruiser I am building now, and working all day in my office at the yard.

The verdict in the first inquest was one of ‘Wilful murder against some person or persons unknown’. It could not be fixed upon the people drowned in the wreck of the bawley, as neither Stenning nor I, nor anyone, could give more than presumptive evidence that the bawley we had come upon not far from the Eddystone had anything to do with the affair. So the thing rested till the inquest on the bodies from the wreck was held, over at Pentressan, some days afterwards.

And that produced little but identification. Three bodies were washed up within five miles of the coast, and it seems reasonable to suppose that that is all there were. The cause of death in every case was drowning.

The first was a young man called Peter Marston. He was twenty–three years of age, and had left Cambridge about ten months before. His father came down to identify the body, a grey–haired, venerable old man, from Colchester. He was much cut up. They were people of some means, and the boy since leaving Cambridge, had followed no occupation. He was interested in the fishing industry. The bawley was his property, and he used to cruise in it a great deal, but his father knew little of the companions that he had upon these trips. The father had never before seen any of the other bodies.

The second body was that of a man of between thirty–five and forty years of age, dark haired, wearing a dark suit and boots of continental manufacture. There was no name upon the clothes, but in the pocket there was a love letter from a woman, addressed to Alexander Kura, Poste Restante, Rotterdam. This letter was in a mixture of Russian and German, and bore no address. That was all, except that a small automatic pistol was found in the hip pocket.

The third was a man of about thirty, pale and thin. This man was known to the police, who identified him as an alien called Aukitch, who had been deported from this country for a case of robbery with violence. He was believed to be a Russian Jew.

This inquest was quite short, the verdict being ‘Death from Misadventure’, as I had supposed.

So those inquests passed, a little inconclusively perhaps, but no one had a shadow of a doubt that justice had been done. By that time I had lost interest in a great degree in the inner meaning of the business. I only wanted to be left alone, to get back to my rut and to forget the last six weeks. But I went down one day to the police station when Norman was there, and had a little talk with him about the business.

They had been to Trepwll, and had removed what they had found. They found a barn half full of munitions—thirty–two light machine guns, a number of cheap automatic pistols, a few bombs, and a great amount of ammunition. And they found a farmer who protested that he knew nothing of the contents of his barn, and they were forced to the conclusion that he spoke the truth. He had leased his barn to a man called Palmer for the warehousing of goods, and he knew nothing of the nature of the goods inside the packing cases. He knew that some of them were carpet sweepers, because he had seen the labels.

The police had removed what they had found, and had contrived to hide the matter from the Press.

And there the matter, Norman said, must rest till after the election, now only a fortnight off. There was no evidence at all of any destination of the arms; they had been brought to the barn and stored, and no one from the district had been near the place. At the Yard they suspected that the arms had come from Russia, and they were certain that the introducers of the arms were dead, drowned in the bawley. He agreed that there must be some local agent in the Glanferis district who had some knowledge of the business, but so far they had found no trace of him. And, acting on instructions from above, they did not intend to prosecute their search for him just at the moment.

“Frankly,” he said, “I think this is the end of the affair.”

I thought about it for a minute. “It may be,” I said at last, “but I don’t see how you come to that conclusion all the same. You’ve not discovered anything about the directing intelligence behind it all.”

He smiled a little. “That depends on how you look at it,” he said. “Do you doubt that the directing intelligence was Russian in its origin?”

I shook my head. “No.”

“Well then,” he replied, “there isn’t any question of the origin, essentially. What you mean is that we haven’t found the intermediate agents. I hope that we shall do so in due course. But the important thing is the discovery. For the time we have stopped the importation of the arms, simply because their secrecy has broken down. That gives us breathing space.”

“Till after the election,” I put in, a little cynically.

He shuffled with the papers on his desk. “I have no concern with that aspect of the matter, as you know.”

I went away, and tried to concentrate upon my work for the next few days. Stenning and Joan had gone back to their place in town, tired, I suppose, of the treatment I had given them. And I went on living in my house alone, working all day and drinking rather heavily all night, dining alone in a black tie, and sitting after dinner in the library till I could feel that I could face my bed.

And after two or three days I came to the conclusion that I was not satisfied. The police might give this up, but I went over to Plymouth one fine afternoon, driving the Bentley faster than I might have done if I had had a little less to drink at lunch. I went to the accountant who handles my audit, and I said to him:

“See here. Isn’t there some intelligence bureau that you people use? I mean, if you want to find out about anyone? For finding out their credit in hire–purchase matters, and that sort of thing?”

He nodded. “Certainly. I can get you a confidential report on anyone, if you like. It’ll cost you one–and–sixpence in the ordinary way.”

It seemed cheap to me. “That boy called Marston who was drowned the other day,” I said, and I gave his address in Colchester. “I want to know about his women friends.”

He wrinkled his brows. “That’s a little out of the ordinary line,” he objected. “The agency will handle it all right, but it may cost you a bit more. You want their names, social position and that sort of thing?”

I nodded. “That’s exactly it. I want a list of all the women he knew well, who would have gone about with him, alone. Their addresses, and what you can find out about each of them.”

He mused a little. “It’ll probably be one–and–sixpence each,” he said. “Generally takes about two days. I’ll telephone you when it comes to hand.”

And three days later I had the report. There were only two of them, apparently: a waitress in a Cambridge restaurant, and his cousin, Adela Jennings, lately down from Girton. It did not seem to me that the waitress was the one I wanted, and so I concentrated upon Adela.

She lived at Esher, in her parents’ house. I thought about it for a day, wondering if I should meet all Scotland Yard upon the doorstep of that house, and then I took the car and went to London.

I stayed at my club. Nobody I knew was there, and I was disinclined to go and look for anyone. And so I dined very well, alone, and sat alone in the top smoking–room with my cigar and with a magazine all evening, save once, when a waiter brought me whisky and I stopped him by my chair, and he told me about the Test matches, and we talked for a little time. Then he went away, and I sat on with the decanter by the fire, alone. At about three o’clock I went to bed.

Next morning I drove down to the house at Esher in the Bentley. It was a fair–sized place that stood in its own grounds; I drove up to the front door in my car, and rang the bell, and asked to see Miss Adela. They showed me into a morning–room and presently she came to me, an earnest–looking girl in a dark dress with a touch of black in it.

And when I saw her I knew that I had not gone wrong.

I rose to meet her as she came. “Good afternoon, Miss Jennings,” I said grimly. “I’ve come up from Dartmouth to meet you. I want answers to one or two questions, about your cousin and yourself.”

She stared at me, flaming, indignant at my tone. I was standing by the window in bright light, and suddenly she faltered, and the colour died out of her face. And then she whispered: “Oh….”

I stood there eying her. “You seem to know my face.”

She pulled herself together, and said quietly: “I don’t. Who are you, and what are you doing here?”

I smiled, a little cruelly perhaps. “I’m a sojourner,” I said, “as all my fathers were.”

There was a long, restless pause after that. At last she said: “Have you come from the police?”

I stared at her in the eyes. “I’ve come to get answers to my questions,” I said harshly. “True answers, and none of your damn trickery. If you want to know, I’ve come to inquire into a murder.”

She pulled herself together. “I don’t know what you mean.”

I smiled. “Then I’ll explain. You’ve caused the death of five men and a girl, you and your precious friends. I know that much. If you go playing with me any more I shall disclose the whole affair, your part in it as well. You know what that means. Prison for you, and for a damn long spell.”

She sank down on a chair beside the table. “We had considered this,” she said, and as she spoke the tears fell slowly from her eyes. “We knew that if the thing went wrong there would be trouble. It seemed worth it, then. And it has gone most desperately wrong….”

I laughed. “Then I hope it still seems worth it,” I remarked. I turned serious. “You’d better answer my questions. If you don’t, I shall tell all I know. I shall disclose your cousin Peter as the murderous scoundrel that he really was. I shall disclose your part in it.” She had nothing apparently to say to that. “If you tell the truth I’ll go away and leave things as they are, maybe, and you can square your conscience in whatever way you choose to kid yourself.”

I paused. “I’m doing this because I think you saved my life, that night upon the beach. But for that fact I’d blast you up and down the country, in and out of gaol, until I had you dead. I’ll give you this one chance.”

She laid her head down on her arms. “You don’t understand,” she sobbed. “You don’t understand at all.”

“I’m dealing with a pack of murderers,” I said. “I understand that part of it all right.”

“You don’t understand,” she sobbed again. And then she said: “It was all for the election.”

I have had many experiences in the life that I have lived, and sometimes I have been afraid. But I do not think that I have ever before experienced the feeling of sheer horror that came over me when she said that. She had said something utterly incredible. In that one swift moment there came to me all the manœuvrings of the hustlings and the polling booths, the sordid trickery that forms a background to political affairs. I cannot describe in words the feelings that came over me as I stood there and listened to her sobbing at the table, the tense horror of this first hint that all that had been sacrificed and lost was staked upon some move in party politics.

I strode across and knocked her head up from the table. “Just listen here, young woman,” I said angrily. “Now tell me what you mean.”

She sobbed: “It’s true, and now you’ve got it, and I wish that I was dead.”

I said: “What’s this about the election? By God, you’d better speak the truth!”

I held her head up from the table, and I held her tear–streaked eyes with mine. “The guns had to be hidden at Trepwll before the election. And then they were going to be discovered just before the polling day. It was the only way to save the country from the Socialists.”

I let her head drop back upon the table, and she lay there sobbing unrestrainedly. I walked over to the window and stood there for a little time, staring out into the sunlit garden and the rhododendrons. Little by little in my mind the monstrous story fell into its place. Long ago the Zinovieff letter lost an election to the Labour Party; the incredible fact appeared to be that this affair had been conceived as such another. Guns had been brought into the country by some politician of the opposing group, and planted in a disaffected area. I could well see that if these arms had been discovered a few days before the poll and evidence supplied that they had come from Russia, the country would swing solid to Conservative.

One thing was evident; this girl had got to tell me all she knew. I crossed the room to her, and laid my hand upon her shoulder. “Come along,” I said, perhaps a little more gently than I had done up till then. “This thing has gone awry. You tell me this thing is just a fake, a movement in some game of party politics. Six people have been killed in playing it, and now it’s got to stop. More may be killed before it runs its course. Sit up, and tell me how it came about.”

And with a little encouragement she dried her eyes, and told me everything. She had hardly said two sentences before I stopped her with a question.

“Who is the directing influence behind this thing? Who organised it, and paid for it?”

She hesitated.

“Come on, now,” I said harshly. “Out with it. If not, I put it with the police.”

The tears fell from her eyes again. “It was Professor Ormsby,” she replied.

I pulled an envelope and pencil from my pocket to make notes. “Christian names, and address?”

“Charles Hemming Ormsby. He’s a Professor of Political Economy. A Fellow of Nicholas—Cambridge.”

I thought about this for a minute. “Who invented the name for the carpet sweepers—the Greek scholar? Was that him?”

She nodded tearfully. And then, little by little, out it came, until at last I had the whole affair.

I had been shocked by the revelation of the nature of the gun running. I do not know that I was less shocked at the high ideals that lay behind it all, and at the spirit in which it had been carried out. For the root of it lay in a real patriotism and a love of England, distorted but sincere. And here I may say at once that I found no villainy about the thing. Merely an overwhelming vanity, that could not brook another view of what was beneficial for this country that we live in now.

So far as I could understand, Professor Ormsby, the boy Marston, and this girl, his cousin, were the chief participants in the affair. It had no connexion with official Conservatism at all; it could have none, of course. It was a secret enterprise, conceived by Ormsby and carried out by young Marston in his bawley, whose object was to place a Conservative Government in power in England for the next five years. The whole affair had been most cleverly conceived. The guns had come, in fact, from Russian sources, and Russians had co–operated in the smuggling wholeheartedly. I did not hear the details of that part of it—all that had been manœuvred by Professor Ormsby, but the essence of it was that Communism had been invoked in this affair to bring about its own defeat.

In Marston Professor Ormsby had found a resolute young man, secretive and well suited to carry out the detail of his part. The girl had been introduced by Marston at a later date to help him in some business connected with the bawley; I could well imagine that it was a job that called for company of some description. I found strong evidence to lead me to believe that the man they knew as Palmer was Professor Ormsby himself; I do not think that there was anybody else in the affair at all.

If ever people played about with fire it was that little crowd.

Every trip they made they carried Russians to and from the country; almost immediately their smuggling became a means of introducing agents into England who could not get through the immigration barriers. They had been powerless to prevent this traffic, and contented themselves with the knowledge that it would not last for long. From the first their lives were carried in their hands. They served their country secretly, as criminals, and the reward that they were earning was a heavy burden to be carried to their graves. They were out to fool the country for the country’s benefit, and no country takes that sort of trick too well.

The girl knew nothing of events for two or three days prior to the end, but from her knowledge she could reconstruct them well. It was impossible that Marston should have taken part in the murders at my house; he would have been down with the bawley at the entrance to the harbour mouth. I am inclined to doubt, in fact, if he had ever known that violence had been done; there was no occasion for the gunmen to have told him, and every reason why it should be kept from him if they desired to make a getaway. He was the only sailor among them, it is to be presumed.

At last it was all done. I had been there two hours, and for the last hour she had been talking collectedly, giving her evidence in a straightforward way. I had three envelopes of notes; I glanced them over and got to my feet. “That’s all?” I inquired. “If there is anything else whatsoever you’d better tell me now.”

She said that there was nothing more to tell. She asked, a little nervously, what I was going to do.

I stared at her. “God knows.” And then I laughed quietly: “Getting a little bit afraid of your own skin, now, I suppose. Well, you needn’t. If what you say is true, you’re out of it. No worse can happen to you than publicity.”

She faltered. “Will it get into the newspapers?”

“God knows,” I said again. Her question sickened me; for the moment I had been back again in Dartmouth with a braver girl than this. I turned upon her viciously. “There were three of you,” I said. “Between you you murdered two men and a harmless girl. That’s what you’ve done, and you’ll remember it.”

There was a little pause. “One of you three is dead, and I shall see the other soon. And you’ll be left alone to live your time out through the years, with all your memories.” I took my hat from the table. “I must wish you joy of it.”

I drove back up to town and garaged the car, and went back to my club to write. I settled down there in the reading–room, and because I was tired and feeling not so well the stream of tumblers came and went beside my elbow, for the bell was at my side. I wrote on steadily, page after page, and never paused till it was time to drain my glass and go and change for dinner, and then the writing was but half done. And I remember, as I crossed the landing to the stairs, I passed behind two men and heard one say:

“Can nothing be done about that fellow in the reading–room? The boy tells me he’s had seven whiskies in the last two hours, and last night just the same. One doesn’t expect to see that sort of soaking in a club like this.”

I smiled a little and passed on. This was the England Ormsby had set out to fool. The task had not proved very difficult, perhaps.

I dressed with infinite exactitude, and went downstairs and dined alone. It seemed but a moment till I was sitting writing again, and yet I must have lingered over my dinner, for it was nine o’clock when I sat down again in the reading–room. I wrote on steadily into the night, and the little pile of manuscript grew steadily at my elbow, and from time to time the boy came to me again, and went.

At last it was finished. It was very still and silent in the reading–room, still with the silence of an empty London club at night, muffled in repose. I settled down to read my story through, and presently the swing doors parted and closed, and the night porter came to me.

“Will you be wanting anything further tonight, sir?”

I stared at him absently. “What’s the time?”

“Five and twenty past one, sir.”

I shook my head. “You might bring me a few biscuits and a double whisky. I shall be going up in a minute.” And I settled down in the deserted room again.

At last I was finished. I addressed three envelopes: one to Jenkinson and one to Norman, and the third and bulkiest to the editor of the Morning Herald, a paper in which I had a holding at that time. I put all these in one large envelope and sealed them up, and addressed it to Jenkinson: “To be opened in the event of my death.” Then I went to bed.

I suppose I slept that night, but it escapes my memory. I know I heard the clocks chime all the hours of the night, and as soon as it was dawn I pulled my curtains and lay back and tried to read a volume of essays that I had picked up downstairs. And so the night passed, till at last I heard the sound of movement, and I could get up and have my bath.

I put in a trunk call to Cambridge at about nine o’clock and talked for a few moments to the porter at Nicholas. Then I got through to Professor Ormsby, and heard a voice say: “Who is that?”

I smiled a little. “This is Commander Stevenson,” I said, “speaking from London. I must introduce myself on the recommendation of a Miss Adela Jennings, of Esher. I had a most interesting talk with Miss Jennings yesterday over the matter of some carpet sweepers that I believe you are interested in, too. I was wondering if I might come down today—say this afternoon—and have a talk with you about them?”

He had guts, that fellow; there was only the slightest pause. “Certainly,” he said; “I should be very pleased to see you. Shall we say half–past two, in my rooms here?”

“That’s all right for me.”

“Very well, Commander Stevenson,” he replied; “I shall expect you then.” And he rang off.

I had nothing to prepare. At about ten o’clock I left the Club and went and got the Bentley and drove down to Cambridge. It was a lovely day, high summer; in the country it was warm and fresh. I drove with a more contented mind than I had had for many days; looking back upon it now I think that I enjoyed that drive. I was going to a clean–cut issue, going unarmed to meet a man who might be dangerous, with no other weapon but my wits. I was inviolable, for I had nothing left to lose.

I lunched well in Cambridge and went on to Nicholas at the appointed time. The porter took me across the court to a staircase in the southern corner, up some dark stone stairs, and tapped at the door for me. A voice called to me to come in, and I went forward into the room.

He was alone. I found a tall, spare man with very pale blue eyes, a man of perhaps fifty years of age, going a little white about the temples and a little bald on top. It was the room that I had expected I should find, lined with bookshelves on all four walls, and with an oar slung up above the mantelpiece. It was all very quiet and peaceful on that summer afternoon. I close my eyes and I can see it now.

He greeted me cordially enough, and asked me to sit down. He indicated an easychair, but I drew up a chair to the table in the middle of the room and sat down there, resting my arms upon the table and facing him as he stood by the fireplace. “I think we can cut the preliminaries of this quite short,” I said. “I had two hours with Miss Jennings yesterday. She told me a good deal about this gun running, that had not been quite clear to me before.”

He did not deny or argue it; he was too good a man for that. “Exactly,” he said quietly. And then he said: “Before we begin, I should like to know just where your interest lies, if I may inquire? Am I to take it that you represent the police?”

I shook my head. “I come in my own interest.”

He raised his eyebrows a little. “Ah, as a private individual.”

I stared at him grimly. “That is so. It is wiser to leave drunken men alone, you know. Once you start violence things begin to go wrong.”

He nodded slowly. “I think that is so. From the first moment that I heard of that affair I was afraid that trouble might arise from it.” He broke into a smile. “And now it has. I am sure that you will not accuse me of trying to disarm you if I offer my apologies for the treatment you received, in which I had no hand?”

I stared at him. “You are right in fearing that trouble might arise from me. It has. Bad trouble.”

He met my eyes. “I think you had better tell me what you want,” he said quietly.

I considered for a moment. “This is Wednesday,” I said at last. “The country goes to the poll on Friday week, in ten day’s time. On Saturday next, in three day’s time, a story will appear in all the Labour Press which will bring certain charges against you, personally, together with Miss Jennings and the boy Marston, who was drowned. You know the story. You will be accused of having attempted to bias this election with a trick, to swindle the whole of England with faked propaganda in the Conservative interest. That story will be supported with concrete evidence which will bear examination, and it will be true.”

He had gone very white.

I sat there staring at him from behind the table. “I have come to you now,” I said in a hard voice, “because I am merciful. This story will appear on Saturday. I am giving you three days in which to cut the country before you are arrested on a criminal charge.” I paused. “This thing is now in train,” I said. “I mention that, in case you may be thinking of more violence.”

There was a long slow silence in the room. Out in the court through the open window, I could hear a hum of voices, undergraduates going to and fro, and laughter now and then. There was a bee or two about a great bowl of wild flowers in the window seat, and the air was fragrant with the scent of them. And presently he moved forward and sat down at the table opposite me. “Let me explain a little, if I can,” he said.

He thought for a minute, and then he began. And what he gave me was a clear–cut reasoning, as logical as a judgment in the High Court, of the motives which had led him to the action he had taken. He started in and took me, very simply and concisely, through the economic history of England since the war, and he drew parallels all through with the period that came after the Napoleonic wars. I sat there at his table in that summer afternoon and he talked to me as he would have expounded his knowledge to an undergraduate, showing me cause and effect in the kaleidoscope of politics and economic law.

And so he proved to me the essence of his creed. I call it a creed, for it was one to him; I had no doubt of that. On his premises, as he gave them me, it was inevitable that a further Labour Government would bring the country to an irretrievable disaster. He sketched the country as a blind man walking along the edge of a precipice, who follows the contour up and down in little slumps, and always straying nearer to the abyss. He proved this with economic logic that I could not controvert—upon his premises. And so he led me to the centre of his whole belief: that the one duty of a patriot who saw the country with unclouded eyes was to prevent this frightful thing—by fair means or by foul.

He told me that this had come to him a year or more before, and he had justified his implications in the intervening time. He sketched for me, very lucidly, the possible courses that could be taken if the country were to continue with a Labour Government, and he showed me in each case the irretrievable disaster which in each case lay ahead within ten years. And then he went on and told me, very briefly, of the steps which had led him to enlist the services of one of his pupils to prevent this thing, and how the enterprise had been conceived.

It would be idle to deny that he impressed me with his reasoning. He had a keen, clear mind, and much of what he said was pitifully true. I sat there motionless as he was talking, staring out of the window to the bright sunshine of the court. I had lost everything I had to lose in this affair. Had I been altogether wrong in my demand for justice, too severe?

I raised my head, and he was speaking of the course that I had told him I was going to take. “If you do this,” he said, “these things will happen. You must not deceive yourself.” He smiled a little. “I can assure you that I am not thinking of myself, although the prospect of exposure is not … very palatable, I admit. But leave that out. If you expose this matter in the Press, you will be swinging the country solid to the Labour interests, and the consequences which I have outlined to you will occur. That is mere cause and effect.”

He paused. “If on the other hand, you stop this Press campaign, the matter rests as it is. You tell me that no action is to be taken by the police till after the election has passed by. That means that the election will take place without bias in either way. I cannot swing it to Conservative, as I would have done. I am asking you not to swing it to the Labour interest, and I have told you why.”

He stopped speaking, and there was a long silence in the sunlit room. “That lets you out of it all right,” I said cynically. “I see that.” He flushed but did not speak, and I moved over to the window and stood looking down upon the creeper–covered walls and the smooth turf.

And presently I turned to him. “Five men have been killed in this affair, and one girl. Three of the men were your agents, and as murderers of the others they deserved to die. Marston was one of those; if he had not been drowned he’d have been hanged. That is what you made of him.” I paused. “One of the others was your lorry driver, and it may be that he was so involved as to be culpable in this affair.”

I smiled at him, without mirth. “In fact, all your agents have received their punishment, and only you are left.”

He did not speak.

I went on: “But it’s about the last two that I am concerned. You’ve played your fancy game, and you’ve committed murder. You’ve murdered two quite innocent people. One was a police official, a married man with children. They’ll be left pretty badly off. The other was a little dancing girl, from Leeds. She never did you any harm.”

I paused. “I should like to know what you are going to do about these murders, first.”

He inclined his head. “About those”—he hesitated for a moment—“murders, as you call them, nothing can be done, except financially. I should myself refer to them as accidents, in that they were not planned or willed by anyone. In this matter we were playing for a great stake. We were playing for the future of this country and this Empire. You run great hazards when you play for a great stake like that.”

He turned on me. “You must keep a sense of proportion,” he exclaimed. “These deaths are lamentable. But it is this country and this Empire we are dealing with. The issue is the place that Britain takes, the future of the Empire in the world. And you are putting in the scale against all that, a policeman and a dancing girl!

“Think of it, man,” he cried. “A girl that you can pick up for a sovereign in the street! What does one girl of that description matter in a thing like this?”